I am stuck here in Coos Bay after all ...

Day 00300: Friday, 2016 January 01

Today is the day that I change the main weblog index link, which previously pointed to /en/weblog/2015/, to now point to /en/weblog/. This weblog has officially entered multi-year mode.

We spent most of the day working in our mother's classroom again.

Early today, I learned that the plan was to head to Springfield tomorrow to work on cleaning up our former residence, then Vivian and I would head to Portland while our mother would head back to Coos Bay. By the end of the day though, our mother had come up with an excuse to try to get me to come back to Coos Bay. She said that I should help Cyrus with a Boy Scout project that he is going to be working on soon. Until today, I have not been kept in the loop about the project and had not even been told what the project is, but now I find myself volunteered for his clothing drive. I do not even know if he wants help, and I will not be able to speak with him about it until Monday. Meanwhile, my window of opportunity closes tomorrow morning, when we head out, as I will need to have packed or not packed to go to Portland for three weeks.

I say that I do not know if he wants help out of my frustration, but surely he could use the help in reality.

Before finding out that I would not be able to escape, I made a few preparations for the trip. First, I set the home router to stop using my server for DNS. If my server were to go down while I am away, I would not want it to effectively take down the whole network. Next, I forwarded a port from Tor so I would be able to update my weblog while away if I did end up having access to the Internet. However, because this did not work out, I will set the router to use my DNS server again after Vivian is gone.

Having lost hope of getting time away, I once again focused on code. I want to catch every error, no matter how small, so it can be fixed. Sometimes, error messages are less helpful than they could be though, so I decided to build my own error handler. This error handler causes even the most minor error to be fatal and always produce a backtrace. More major errors cannot be caught by the error handler though, so while they are still fatal, they will not produce a backtrace.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Document modifications

On 2018-01-16, my sister, Vivian, requested that I replace all instances of her legal name in my journal with the name "Vivian". She also asked that the name of the organisation she works for be redacted. This page was modified to fulfil that request.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Repairs were needed on the weblog index

Day 00301: Saturday, 2016 January 02

We ended up not going to Springfield today, though Vivian did go home at the end of the day.

The new calendar year page in the weblog directory of this website brought with it several bugs. Most of them were caused by stupid oversights on my part, but it turns out that one of my base functions I built also has a flaw. I consider this error to be caused by ISO-8601. This specification idiotically labels Sunday as the final day of the week instead of the first. PHP's date() function has the ability to use ISO-8601 week numbers, but does not otherwise have any options for distinguishing one week from another. Because of this, I used the ISO-8601 week numbers when building my function and shifted all Sundays one week forward. Normally, this would put Sundays within the appropriate week. However, I did not account for the new year corner case. Specifically, the Sunday supposedly within the week that the year ended is not shifted into the first full week of the year, but is instead shifted into an imaginary week with a week number one higher than the highest real week number. This issue may not be present once I shift my code away from using timestamps, but for now, I have repaired the function so instead of simply adding one to the week number of every Sunday, it instead looks ahead and matches the week number of the Sunday to the following Monday's week number.

After putting my new error handling function into effect, I ran into a bunch of errors relating to the use of dates. Specifically, the option to tell the mkdate() function if daylight savings time is in effect is deprecated. I had always set daylight savings time to not be in effect because daylight savings time is a pain to code around. Without that option available, I simply removed it hoping for the best. This, however, messed up all entry numbers involving dates that fell within daylight savings time, causing them to become non-integers due to that one hour difference between the time stamps that were expected and those that were received. I managed to hack together a fix, but it is only a hack. The only clean option is to ignore daylight savings time, as it only throws things off and that level of precision is not needed or wanted. Of course, if the world was not idiotically setting their clocks forward and backward each year, PHP would not be imitating this nonsense and there would be no issue to build around.

I started work on the onion address-finding spider again, this time adding a timeout feature to work around this one page that never finishes loading. Seriously, last time I ran my spider script, I waited hours and the spider could not get past this one page. It could not have been continually sending data like a huge page, as the spider did not hit the download limit and abort. I also increased the download length limit in the configuration of my own copy of the spider in hopes of getting a different page to download successfully. This page is huge, but it is a regular Web page containing only a multitude of hyperlinks. At the time I went to bed, the spider had not completed its crawl, but it seemed to have made great progress. Unless there is an unexpected error, I expect it to complete tomorrow.

I started work on a couple new wrapper classes while waiting for the spider to finish its task, but I did not complete them. Due to the FrontBase functions having two types of resources to work with, the two classes are a bit entangled and one should not be considered completed until the other is. For one of the classes, I experimented with class constants and a switch statement. I decided that due to the way type juggling is implemented in PHP, I thought it best to avoid including one and zero in the list of integer values used by the constants.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Document modifications

On 2018-01-16, my sister, Vivian, requested that I replace all instances of her legal name in my journal with the name "Vivian". She also asked that the name of the organisation she works for be redacted. This page was modified to fulfil that request.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Does my spider finally work?

Day 00302: Sunday, 2016 January 03

Even after over twelve hours, my onion address-crawling spider was not moving on past another certain address. I had to give up and abort the spider's process. I had thought that I had written the script to abort each download after an hour of trying, but after further reading, I think that the setting that I used only pertained to the amount of time needed to initiate a server connection. Once connected, the server was allowed to cause as long of a hang as it wanted to! I modified the code to use CURLOPT_TIMEOUT instead of CURLOPT_CONNECTTIMEOUT, so now, hopefully the bot will not allow any Web page to cause a hang that lasts longer than an hour. When I finally went to bed, it was still running. I will check on it in the morning.

Wowaname has set up an onion address for her clearnet website. This got me thinking. When I learned that IANA had set aside the //onion. TLD for official use by Tor, I started linking to onion addresses as I would other addresses. However, until today, I have still linked to clearnet addresses ahead of onion addresses when both were available, due to the fact that these addresses can be used by Tor users and non-Tor users alike. I need to stop treating onion addresses as second-class addresses. Onion addresses are officially completely legitimate. I need to encourage Tor use by linking to onion addresses whenever they are available.

Wowaname also removed services from the Volatile network. I think that maybe she realized that she was abusing her power when she was trolling theunknownman. She had been taking advantage of the fact that she runs the network and services, using more force than a regular user is able to, despite the fact that she has always been against people doing such.

People on #Volatile were talking about how annoying it was that many users supposedly support Tor, but get annoyed at Tor users when said Tor users are not able to access sites that the non-Tor users want to show them. These websites are maliciously discriminating against Tor users, yet it is the Tor users that are made out to be the bad guys. In particular, paste sites that participate in such descrimination were mentioned, so I brought up the fact that I had been meaning to build a paste site that runs on an onion address. Seeing that, z showed me an existing paste site: Anon PasteBin. While I will still use Debian Pastezone whenever I am working in a context that I believe is seen by more clearnet users than Tor users, if I think that Tor use is the standard in a given context, I will use Anon PasteBin instead now. There are two things that I do not like about Anon PasteBin though. First, using it requires solving a CAPTCHA, unlike Debian Pastezone. Second, the default deletion setting is to never delete e given paste, again, unlike Debian Pastezone. Anon Pastebin does allow one to set an expiration tome, however.

I went off to work with my mother in her classroom again today. On the way there, we stopped at a store, so I picked up the mobile service activation card I needed to begin service on my secondary device. Much to my dismay, they charged me an extra dollar for an "E911 tax". First of all, they should have built that into the price. Instead of tacking on the tax as an extra charge, they should have just raised the price of the product to cover the tax. At least that way, I would know the real price of what I was buying before I bought it.

After we left the store, we spent most of the day working in her classroom. While there, I got a couple of leads on jobs though. First, one of the teachers said that the school is always in need of aids and that perhaps I could apply. She did not know the details of what qualifications I would need in order to become an aid, but it is worth looking into. A second teacher said that she thought that becoming an aid required specific collage courses be taken first. She recommended looking for work at a computer repair store run by a couple she trusts though. She said that she had no idea if they were hiring though, so there is no guarantee that a job is even available there.

Speaking of computer repair, Vanessa and Cyrus returned home today. While away, Cyrus made the mistake of letting his friends pressure him into trying to install Skype. Somehow, the attempt borked his whole system. The most obvious issue was that his display managed was broken. He though that he had "uninstalled his GUI", but the startx command brought Xfce up. I found that the lightdm package was still present, but in some sort of half-installed limbo state. I could not fully install it though because it required missing dependencies be installed and we could not get the machine to connect to the network, neither via Wi-Fi nor Ethernet. I tried to take a look at the network manager, but I found that that too was in some sort of half-installed limbo state and dealing with unresolved dependencies. After much struggle, We decided to back up his personal files and reinstall the system from scratch. Fixing the current system installation would require a network connection, but acquiring a network connection would require first fixing the system. We backed up his files tonight, but we will have to work on reinstalling the system tomorrow.

I honestly tried to get my IRC server set up today, but there simply was not time. I uninstalled both ngIRCd and Atheme services, then installed Ratbox. That was as far as I got though. When I get a chance, I need to configure Ratbox, then look into Ratbox services.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

This is utter madness

Day 00303: Monday, 2016 January 04

I awoke this morning expecting to see not that the onion spider had completed its task, but instead, that it had discovered a whole new wave of URIs to check out. While I am excited to know that it is finding a lot of URIs, it has been quite bothersome being unable to see how much further the spider has left to travel. I have now added a line of output to each iteration that displays the current time (useful to know how long a page has been hanging), the number of URIs that have already been traversed, and the number of URIs currently in the queue. While the number of URIs in the queue is not the same as the number of URIs left to traverse, it is the best approximation of it. I will be unable to see this new feature in action until the next run of the spider though.

I walked into the local community collage today, as they just got off break. A week before break, they said that they would talk to the person I need to schedule an appointment with so I could get an appointment set up, but they never got back to me. After getting there, I had to wait in several lines, each time being directed to yet another. At one point, I even got sent back to wait in a line that I had already waited in! I discovered that the reason that they had not gotten back to me via email is that before they can help, I have to pay a $40 USD fee and fill out some paperwork, even if I do not end up taking any classes whatsoever. So do they tell me this via email so I can actually know what is going on? No. Instead, they just stop responding. In fact, because of this, I have missed the first day of the current term, which was today. They will still accept registrations until Wednesday, but there is not a discount for the missed days of class; I would be paying for them even though they had caused me to miss them. Next term ends in June, and I do not even know if I will still be in this town at that point.

While I was out, I came up with how I want to implement /robots.txt file support. Before I could build the class that I need for this /robots.txt file support, I needed to finish the two wrapper classes I started two days ago, in order to keep up my goal of including at least one wrapper class in each library code update. Reluctantly, I headed back to the PHP manual to research the FrontBase functions, but on the way, I found that PHP 7 reserves several new words. It seems pretty obvious what most of these words are being reserved for. These words will probably be used for type hinting! This will be awesome. Right now, only three types of type hints can be used. You can specify that the parameter is supposed to be an array, supposed to be callable, or supposed to be an object of a class of your choosing. If you want to accept, for example, an integer as an argument, you must also accept, for example, a string. The three new reserved words that are somewhat odd are true, false, and null. The only use for these that i can think of is the same thing that they are used for now. They act as strange constants that are automatically defined in every name space. I do not see what function they would be used for outside of this. Perhaps this bizarre type of constant is to be removed in PHP 7, so reserved words are needed to perform the function that the bizarre constants once did. I finished work on the wrapper classes, but I had no time to work on the /robots.txt file support class. I should probably get the MySQL wrapper class finished as well before I continue work on the spider. The next time that the spider is run, it should be both respecting /robots.txt files and saving to an actual database.

I tried setting up Ratbox, but I could not get it started. It kept silently dying during startup. No error messages were displayed on the commend line and I could not find any relevant lined in the system log. I eventually had to give up, being unable to reach the main Ratbox support group and being unable to find another Ratbox support group. I think that I will quit trying to get an IRC server set up for the time being.

My mother continues to push that I try to get enrolled this term, despite my feelings against it. First of all, I will miss the beginning of class and still have to pay for it. But more importantly, as I already told her, I should finish paying off my school loans, save up to go back to school, *then* go back to school. I should *not* go back to school while still in debt, requiring even more loans to do so and sinking further into debt. She insists that I telephone the school tomorrow for more information, again, disregarding the fact that I absolutely hate working with telephones. I refuse to do it. The way I see it, she has her choice of two options. She can either choose how a task is completed by completing it herself, or she can choose to delegate the task, at which point the one she delegates to is free to complete the task in the manor of his/her choosing. I have emailed the school tonight to ask for the information, but as they do not seem to answer emails and time is short, I will also walk back into the school tomorrow. I have also written to my old school and asked about how to get an official copy of my transcript sent to the school and an unofficial copy downloaded for reference in the mean time. I have no way to know if they will send the unofficial copy in time to make a reasonable decision as far as choosing classes is concerned, but I doubt that they will. Likewise, there is no time to get financial aid, and assuming all my credits are good toward a degree, there is no room for me to take extra courses without them being pointless wastes of money. In theory, I am only one course away from the associate degree that they can provide. This is utter madness. My mother is mad.

I chanced upon a Tor node status website in my continuing onion spider output on the command line. It was pretty easy to find my node as well. When I went to bed, the spider seemed to be about halfway through the wave of onion addresses that it began yesterday, assuming that most of the addresses in memory are as alphabetically organized as they appear to be. I estimate that it will finish with this wave in two days, though there may be another wave coming after that. I believe though that the onion addresses it has in memory are mostly-alphabetized not due to my sorting (which does not occur until the end of its process) but due to it having read Harry71's alphabetized onion list. The first real wave of onion addresses came from a reading of his list, after which, each of his listed onions was queried, but only for the page that he linked to: the main index page. During this first wave, the spider built up a bigger address list by reading all the hyperlinks on those index pages. This bigger list is the second wave of queries, and I assume that most of it is composed of the index pages linking to other pages on the sites that they represent. Because most of the links are internal, the spider's address queue remained mostly-alphabetical. I can only assume though that the index pages do not link to every page within the sites, so more waves are likely to arrive. I have no idea how many and I have no idea when this spider will finally complete its task. It would be very helpful to be able to use the new progress-reporting feature I added today, but that would involve halting the spider and completely erasing the progress that it has made already.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

/robots.txt file support is needed before I can continue

Day 00304: Tuesday, 2016 January 05

I awoke this morning to two surprises. First, the community college had written back to me. However, they only wrote back one sentence, a sentence telling me that I had to telephone a particular department of the school for information. I wrote back that I do not have telephone service, and asked if there is an email address that I can reach that department at, though I could not depend on them to get back to me by the time my mother gets home, nor could I depend on their next response to bring answers. I have to walk into the school as planned. I only really wrote back in order to hopefully get them to think about the fact that not everyone has telephone service. If someone writes in via email, throwing telephone numbers at them just is not very nice. Likewise, if someone were to telephone in, throwing email addresses at them would not be very nice. It did pay off to write back though. Before heading out, they sent the email address that I needed. I wrote to the department that I needed information from, but again, I could not depend on a timely reply, so I headed out. I did receive an automated reply to them though, saying that they would respond within three business days, which would be far too late. At least the department that I have to contact is one that I had to deal with in-person yesterday. I know exactly where they are.

The second surprise that I awoke to was that my onion spider had completed the wave of URIs that it had been working on and had started working on the next. The most recent output from the spider seemed to be from a forum, so I decided to check it out. As it turns out, VFEmail has their own onion address! I knew that they did not deliberately block or hinder Tor users, which is why I use their service for my secondary inbox. However, it seems that this is a conscious decision to support Tor use, not just a simple lack of malice toward Tor users. If you expect to stay on the onion though, you need to be aware that some of the hyperlinks there, such as the main link to the forum, use full URIs, causing them to point to the clearnet forum address from both the clearnet and onion domains. Furthermore, according to their privacy and security page, they actively recommend using both PGP and Tor when sending and receiving emails.

The people at the school informed me that the discount my mother wants information on is only available to to educators working at the community college, not educators working in any school anywhere. I also wrote to my old school again trying to get a copy of my transcript so I can have some idea of what courses I need in order to finish my degree at the local community college. THere is only one course that I know for sure that I am in need of.

While I was at the school, I saw a strange and faded flier. It was one of those ones with the strips cut in the bottom so that you could take someone's contact information, but the main body of the flier said to take what you need and the strips at the bottom had various things that someone may need emotionally, such as "a hug", "happiness", and "love". I looked through the remaining ones, doubting that there was one I would feel was worth taking, but it turns out that there was one for me after all: "freedom". I do not know what I will do with the strip, but I found it reassuring that the person designing the flier felt that someone would be in need of freedom. But why was this flier put up in the first place?

When I got home, I found that the onion spider was working with a website that liberates copyrighted works that are behind pay walls. While this does not nullify the copyrights, so this work cannot be reused, at least those required to read it by their schools and such may not have to pay such immoral hoarders of information if they find this site.

I found a package in the Debian repository that contains the PHP documentation. I replaced the copy that I had downloaded from the PHP website with this package, but it seems that this version of the documentation is missing all of the hyperlinks in the resource types section. The copy downloadable from the main PHP website is easier to navigate.

I considered converting my wrapper classes into traits. This would allow a class to leverage multiple resource types. For example, I could have my /robots.txt-handling class implement features from both the MySQL wrapper class and the cURL wrapper class. That way, it could store and read data in and from a MySQL database, so it would not need to redownload /robots.txt files that it had already worked with on a previous URI if those /robots.txt had been retrieved within a set period of time, while also being able to retrieve /robots.txt files that were stale or had not yet been retrieved. However, traits cannot be directly instantiated. The wrapper classes should not require extension before use.

I looked into building a MySQL wrapper class so I could continue work on my spider. However, it seems that the modern MySQL API is already object-oriented like it should be. I might refrain from building a wrapper class for the old MySQL API due to the fact that it has been removed from PHP 7. If I take the time to build it, I will just need to delete it later when Debian Stable upgrades to PHP 7.

I chanced upon a website that distributes books, though I am not sure if it is legal or not. The reason that they exist though is because common ebooks are too restrictive. The website administrator could not find ebooks that were not both encumbered by DRM and more expensive than paper books, so he/she set up a website in which such books were available.

When I finally got to speak with my mother about the information I had about the community college, I was able to push things into my favor a bit. I first explained the fact that the school had said that the educator discount does not apply to her. I am hoping that she realizes that this means that the extreme rush that she is putting on this is unwarranted, even if she cannot see the fact that it is counterproductive. I next explained that my old school still has not gotten back to me about my transcript. I cannot be sure of what courses I need until I have it. Finally, I showed her the degree program information page that I had picked up at the school yesterday. On the page, it looks like the one course that I know I need is not available to take this term. The only course that I know is actually necessary must wait until next term. I do not think that she has processed all of this enough to stop the push altogether, but she did start focusing on next term instead of this one, which gives me some room to breath and some time to prepare.

I started work on the spider again, but quickly found that I have not done enough planning yet, so I cannot set up my two tables. One table will be for Web page information found by the spider. I am not too worried about getting this table wrong at first, as the spider will start with a simple table and simple features, then expand its capabilities and need a table with more fields. Of more concern to me is the table used to store /robots.txt information. This table will need to store information from /robots.txt files in a usable way. I cannot really continue until the table layout is figured out. The spider's code is currently in a broken state and unusable. I will work on planning the /robots.txt file database more tomorrow.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

The spider is almost usable again

Day 00305: Wednesday, 2016 January 06

The search engine spider was quickly filling up my RAM and my machine was getting a bit hot, or so I thought. I felt that the best option was to terminate the spider for now. However, after terminating the spider, I found that my RAM was still mostly in use. I terminated the spider and lost days worth of information for nothing! My RAM was probably just in use because my system was being efficient. The thing that I had not taken into account is that a reasonable system will try to use most of the RAM. RAM that is not being used is RAM that is not serving a function. By filling the RAM with information from current processes, the system is able to load those processes quicker. If more RAM is needed later, a reasonable system will clear the less-needed junk out of RAM to make room for things that are needed. I have no reason to believe that Debian is not such a reasonable system, just trying to make the most of the hardware that is available. I will run the spider again once I have implemented some new features and am not running as much of it in RAM. For now, it is in a broken state, so I cannot restart it yet.

I have some thinking about how to store /robots.txt information and have come to the conclusion that I should not store it between crawls at all. At the point the spider is recrawling a page, it is considering the possibility that changes have been made. Changes too could have been made to the /robots.txt file, so it should be re-retrieved. However, if multiple pages are retrieved from the same website during a single crawl, the /robots.txt file should only be downloaded once. The indexed data from the last crawl should be alphabetized, but newly-found pages will be out of order. I do not know how well storing all the parsed /robots.txt files in RAM would be though, so I think that I will only store one /robots.txt file at a time. This will be very inefficient during the first crawl, but later crawls should not involve too many extra /robots.txt file downloads. With this new perspective in mind, I wrote a class that handles standard User-agent: and Disallow: directives in addition to Allow: and Sitemap: directives. At some point, I would like to add sitemap support to the spider, though I have not added that today. My plans were to implement the blacklisting feature far later in the development process, but I decided to build it today, along with the function needed to implement it. Basically, this new function normalizes onion addresses before hashing them. This allows the spider to interpret a blacklist on a particular onion address as applying to all subdomains of that onion as well. If something is bad enough that it needs to be blacklisted, we can assume that the whole onion should be removed from the search results. For convenience, the function takes a whole URI as input, though it only uses the domain of the URI to determine the hash result. I found though that the progress report feature I added yesterday is no longer usable. It relies on the in-RAM arrays that I just removed from the code. I do not know if I will be able to build a similar feature when using a MySQL database. I got most of the new logic set up, but I did run into an issue near the end and had to give up for the night. I need a way to SELECT URIs from the `anchors` table, but only SELECT URIs that are not present in the `titles` table.

I tried to contact my old school again about getting a copy of my transcript. They still have not responded to me.

We found something a bit annoying about the air here in Coos Bay. Because it is wetter than the air in Springfield, our perishable food is becoming inedible faster. We will have to keep this in mind for the future.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

It is alive!

Day 00306: Thursday, 2016 January 07

It seems that I finally found an email address at my old school that people actually respond to. They told me how to buy a copy of my transcript, but it requires logging into my old university account. However, due to my data loss about a year ago, I do not have my old password. I cannot perform a password reset either, due to having lost the passwords to my old email address and the password for the domain registrar account under which the domain of my old email address had registered. My old domain has expired too, so that email address is permanently out of reach for me. I wrote back, but as soon as I got up this morning and saw the email from them, but I did not receive another answer today. I will have to hope that they respond again tomorrow.

It turns out that the answer to my problem with the spider yesterday is a join query. After getting past that snag, development went mostly well, though a few other issues did pop up. I feel like I got a lot of work done on the spider today, but somehow, I do not have a lot to say about it. Mostly, I am just thinking about where to go from here. In any case, the spider is now storing its data completely in a MySQL database instead of a flat file. Not much data is stored in RAM either, so if the spider is interrupted, not much data is lost. The spider keeps track of when the last time it crawled a page though, so it will not re-request the page that it was interrupted when crawling. I think that I came up with a fix for that while writing this entry, but it is too late to implement it for this particular crawl. The issue is that the data for the page itself is written to the database before the hyperlinks are found and recorded. I can fix this, but if I interrupt the spider to do so, the data will have already been written to the database and the damage done. I need to let the spider finish before trying to do anything to the running instance. Knowing that it will take several days to finish its work, there is no rush, so I will work on the fix for the issue tomorrow and test it on newdawn. (The main instance is now running on cepo.) This time will also give me a chance to plan how I want to make the search interface even work. Until I have a plan in regards to how to perform searches, I cannot have the spider gather any data that is actually useful outside of finding more pages to crawl. For now, the data it gathers is fairly useless because all it knows is that pages have been linked to.

My mother was given a chance to apply to switch which grade level she is teaching at her school. I asked her if she was going to take that opportunity, but she decided to be very vague, so I do not know what she plans to do.

Cyrus' Boy Scout project plan involving a clothing drive was declined due to the fact that it was not flashy enough. It would not draw attention to the Boy Scout brand much. Instead, he was asked to plan some sort of park cleanup instead. While the clothing drive would do more good for the community, the park cleanup will draw more attention. I think that this really shows that the Boy Scouts are not as good of an organization as people think that they are.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

An error in the handling of relative URIs

Day 00307: Friday, 2016 January 08

I awoke this morning to find that the spider had choked on a bad URI that it had pulled from its own database. It assumes that all URIs in its database are valid, but somehow, it had managed to put an invalid URI there. Before attempting to diagnose the problem, I made sure to check my email to see if the school had written me back though. They had not. With that out of the way, I ran a query against the database to find the offensive page so that I could run tests on my merge_uris() function, which had to have returned invalid results for this to happen. The link was to https://5jp7xtmox6jyoqd5.onion, so I just searched for the page that linked to it. Only one result came up: http://52wdeibt3ivmcapq.onion/darknet.html. This page contains many technically-invalid URIs that my spider should have successfully sanitized. Or rather, my merge_uris() function should have successfully sanitized them. Running another query against the database, I found that this page alone had been allowed to add eight URIs with no path component to my database; URIs that are technically invalid and which, by feature, not bug, would choke merge_uris() when used as the "absolute URI" parameter of that function. But before reaching the database, they should have been given as the "relative URI" parameter, causing the function to return the URI with a slash at the end, making the URIs valid. To make sure that it was in fact a bug in the function and not the spider, I tested the function on every invalid URI that the page had added to my database. The function returned the expected incorrect result every time.

I added a call to \var_dump() right before the return statement, but it was not getting executed. Searching for another spot where the function returns, I immediately found the problem. If the relative URI has a different scheme that the absolute URI that it is merged with, the relative URI is assumed to be absolute. In theory, this should be accurate. If the scheme is different, relative URIs should not be used at all, so the hyperlink should point to an absolute URI. In practice though, some webmasters do not respect this, or even do not know it. It does not help that many Web browsers stupidly hide the path of a URI when the path is only a slash. All this does is breed ignorance that the URI even has the trailing slash, resulting in more people writing bad hyperlinks, such as those on the page that messed up my database. That said, my function should account for bad input as well, at least if the bad input is said to be a relative URI. This function's whole purpose is to take incomplete URIs and make them whole in an automated way. I think I managed to fix the function, then I used a short script to repair the damage to the database so I would not have to throw out the whole database.

In the process of scanning the database for errors, I found several erroneous IRC URIs, which got me thinking. At some point, I should scan the database and see how many onion-based IRC networks I can find.

Upon the next run of the spider, I found that it was requesting FTP and Gopher pages. I thought that I had implemented a protocol whilelist and only allowed HTTPS- and HTTP-based URIs, but it seems that I neglected to make the spider actually check the whitelist. That means that the spider will be requesting pages that it does not know how to handle yet. However, because of the new logic flow that allows use of the MySQL database, if I fix the protocol whitelist feature, the spider will look endlessly.

Having needed to update my base library, I put aside work on the spider, despite its current issues, to work on a wrapper class, as I had agreed to include at least new wrapper class in every update. I have also decided to restructure the library version numbers a bit. Currently, the version numbers are increasing quickly, making it look like I am making more progress on it than I am. I will also be holding the version numbers back a bit until progress catches up with the version number. After building the FDF wrapper class, I started work on a FTP wrapper class. I found though that some FTP functions rely on file resources, so I would need to complete a file wrapper class first. However, for this wrapper class, I would need a wrapper class for stream resources. Looking into stream resources, I found that there is a documented prototype for implementing stream objects. My understanding of this class prototype though is that it does not meet my goals. Instead of wrapping up a stream resource with its related functions, it instead replaces stream resources altogether. I might try creating a class that both implements this prototype and wraps up the functions I want wrapped up. This class prototype though, and probably stream resources in general, requires stream context support, so I moved on and built the a class wrapping stream context resources.

For my own reference, current work that needs to be done on the spider includes:

find a way to avoid trying to crawl uncrawlable URIs without creating an endless loop
replace mis-implemented protocol whitelist with a switch() statement to allow handling different protocols in different ways
restructure program flow to cause <a/>s to be scanned for and saved before the <title/> is recorded to make spider interruptions to no longer be detrimental
Fix handling of <a/>s that have child nodes

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

\scandir()

Day 00308: Saturday, 2016 January 09

For some strange reason, my spider keeps quitting on me without an error message. At least now, quitting does not cause all the data to be lost.

I found a function in the PHP manual that I had not seen before: scandir(). This function lists all files in a directory, and even does it alphabetically. As far as I can tell, the only thing that directory handles and \Directory object are good for is listing directories, so this simple function obsoletes both, as both are a pain to use. Literally every time that I want to use them, I have to consult the manual again to be sure I am using them correctly because you cannot just iterate over them as expected. Instead, you must explicitly check each return value for being identical to (not just equal to) false while at the same time assigning the values to variables. I have always thought that such a directory-listing function should exist, but could never find it, so I always just built my own. This function also obsoletes my own custom dir() function, which just creates a dir object, iterates over it, then alphabetizes and returns the results, so I am removing it. It obsoletes my dir class as well, though I will be keeping that due to it being one of my wrapper classes.

While working on wrapping stream resources, I found some interesting things. First, that class prototype that I found yesterday seems to be for use with the stream_wrapper_register() function. It is completely irrelevant to my current project of wrapping up resources with their function. Second, and more interestingly, I do not see any functions for actually creating a stream resource. Instead, as best I can tell, the stream functions are used on resources created by more specific functions. For example, I think that the stream functions apply to directory resources and FTP resources. I was thinking about making my stream class into an abstract class for other classes such as the FTP class to extend, but there is a small issue with that plan. Specifically, my directory class already extends the default, half-implemented \Directory class. I can instead make it into a trait, though that means reworking several classes. Specifically, my wrapper classes currently use self::$resource to hold the resource handle, but \Directory uses self::$handle instead. In order to make the trait work, I will need to change any class that uses the stream trait to match. For consistency, I will probably change all the wrapper classes to match whether they use the stream trait or not. The one down side to using a trait instead of an abstract class is that I cannot use type hints to require that certain function take only resource wrappers as arguments. From the looks of it though, if this becomes a problem, I can create an interface to go with the trait. An interface cannot define working methods and a trait cannot be used for type hinting, but together, they can get the job done.

I ran into some strange functions relating to "bucket objects" and "brigade resources". There is no documentation that I can find on where brigade resources come from or how to create them. The only scrap of information that I can find is on the \stream_bucket_prepend() function's documentation page. This documentation says that a brigade resource is a resource used to contain bucket objects, but that is all that is says bout them. As for bucket object, I ran some tests on my machine, and it seems that bucket objects are just \stdClass objects that have three properties: a string, an integer, and a "userfilter.bucket" resource. I am also having trouble wrapping the stream_socket_*() functions, as their descriptions are not consistent. Some appear to work on a specific type of resource that is used for socket streams, but some imply that they are for streams in general.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

include.d

Day 00310: Monday, 2016 January 11

When I uploaded my PHP function and class library, I did not really have a name for it, so I just put it in a repository called php. I think that I know what I want to officially call it now though: "include.d". Being that it actually has a name now though, I think that I will reset the version number as well and call the next release version zero of include.d. I will wait until I have something to update before reseting the version and assigning the name though.

On #Volatile, z showed me a very nice new font! I never could get my machine to recognize it though, so I have not been able to make use of it yet. I will keep trying as time allows.

People disgust me sometimes. On #Debian, someone was asking for help installing Debian Unstable. Instead of trying to be helpful, one user kept advising that if one does not already know how to install Debian Unstable, one should ne be given instructions for installing it. But by that logic, no one can ever learn! Luckily both someone else and I were around to actually provide information. Installing Debian Unstable is not hard, but it does require a small amount of prior knowledge. All you have to know though is that there is no Unstable installer, so once you install Stable, you need to modify your source list to point at the Unstable repositories. Honestly, is it too much to ask that people try to help each other instead of trying to discourage each other from performing even simple tasks?

I have given up on my search engine plans. The simple fact is that I do not have the disk space needed to gather enough information to make search queries at all functional. Instead, I will just put together an onion address index. I need to add another table to make this work, but I will will make a list of only the main index pages of websites in onion space. I think that it would be wise to have the list output to a private place that only I can read, do a shallow search for illegal stuff to blacklist, rebuild the list, then publicize it.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Moving forward again

Day 00311: Tuesday, 2016 January 12

Yesterday, I got almost nothing done, programing-wise. I think the problem is that I sat to work on boring wrapper classes and only boring wrapper classes. I wanted to make some progress on that so that I could be done with it sooner, but I need to throw in some actual usable stuff in between. I should focus more on my spider and only put the minimal effort that I promised into the wrapper classes. The wrapper classes will not be needed for quite some time, and if any of them become relevant before they are written, I can simply jump ahead and write the needed wrapper class. This should keep me more motivated to actually keep my code moving forward.

As the first order of business today, I fixed the issue in which the spider will not recrawl the page that it was interrupted while crawling, though that will not help until the next time that it is interrupted or reaches the end of the current crawl. I forgot to yesterday though that the spider keep getting interrupted every time that my laptop disconnects from the server, even when I use the disown command or & operator, so I was able to deploy the fix fairly quickly. The spider takes longer to start up as it gathers more information though, and I always worry that I have introduced bugs such as those that might prevent any output at all. At one point, I caused the spider to loop endlessly, so I added a few debug information output lines so that I can see where the script is looping. It is a relief to be able to see the difference between a hang in the script versus an unending loop with no output. The spider hung for hours this time when I started it though, and I ended up adding even more debug lines. As it turns out, my database has gotten too big for the spider to effectively query, and thus, the spider cannot know where to crawl next. I thought that I would be fine if I simply did not hang onto information needed for search engine queries, but it seems that even holding onto data used by the spider itself is too much. I have had to downsize what the spider stores, making it a bit less effective. Now, it will only store information about website index pages. It will have to depend on websites having internal links that make everything accessible from the main index, though it can take several hops if needed. If a found URI relates to a page on the same site, it will be crawled looking for more links to external sites, but if the found URI is found that points to a different website's page, the URI will be truncated to the root directory and stored in the database.

I felt completely lost as to whether I need to rework the way that the crawling and database work first or implement support for other protocols first. In the end, I decided to learn more about the protocols so that I can parse the responses that I get from the servers. After I have built the tools that I need in order to understand server responses, I will set up the switch() statement for dealing with URIs of different schemes differently, rework the HTTPS/HTTP-handling code, and add the support of other schemes that cURL can handle. I started out by learning Gopher directory-listing syntax. With some help from someone that prefers not to be mentioned, as well as some queries to a known Gopher server, I was able to decypher the very basic syntax. As it turns out, Gopher directory listings are listings of resources on the same server, a different server, or a mix. Gopher only allows linking to three types of servers though, assuming I understand correctly: Gopher servers, Telnet servers, and tn3270 servers, with tn3270 being an ancient form of Telnet that has its own URI scheme. There is a hacky workaround that allows linking to arbitrary URIs, but it seems very messy to me. Basically, it is implemented as a link to an HTML page that is on the same server as the directory listing, but the text of the link has a specific syntax. The client is expected to recognize that because the specific syntax is being used, the link is not actually to be taken at face value. The "server" and "port" information of the link is to be ignored, and information from the link text is to be used instead. If the client fails to understand this, it will request the HTML file that the link actually points to, though as a fallback, the HTML file sent to the client when it does so will usually be an HTML redirection page that redirects the client to the correct URI. I do not like this special-case-type syntax, and will probably have the spider ignore it by simply not programming it to recognize the special case. I assume that the HTML redirect pages used use <meta/> refresh tags, so Gopher's use of those may prompt me to work on support for <meta/> refresh tags at some point soon. This support would apply to XHTML/HTML pages retrieved over HTTPS/HTTP as well. The other oddity in the Gopher directory listings is the informational message links. This links have a dummy host name and dummy port, due to the fact that they are not meant to to be links at all. However, as Gopher directory listings can contain only links, the only way to provide non-link information is by using such dummy information. Next, I looked into FTP support. FTP seems to return a directory listing of the files actually contained in a directory. There is no title information present though, and as far as I know, FTP is not typically used to set up website-like pages the way that Gopher is, so I will not find XHTML files with links to other sites. There is really no reason for me to crawl these pages. I might put such services that do not need to be crawled in a separate database than the services that should be crawled. I kind of wonder if I want the spider to crawl anything *besides* HTTPS, HTTPS, and Gopher pages. Other types of resources might be good to query for a name, such as IRCS servers, but I doubt that they will need to be recursively crawled.

It appears that wowaname's hosting service has gone down for the time being. She left her computer at her roommate's house over winter break due to not having a stable Internet connection at home and her roommate's older brother unplugged the machine. From the sound of it, wowaname's hosting is usually provided over her school's Internet connection. They do not mind if students use this connection for whatever they like, such as providing hosting services, but they do not allow students to keep anything plugged in over the break.

Cyrus has less than two weeks before his time is up and it is too late for him to complete his Boy Scout project. He was going to have me run some paperwork around town while he is in school tomorrow to save himself some time, but opted against it, saying that he had more that needed to be done before the paperwork could be dealt with. I wish that there was something I could do to help take the stress off of him a bit, but every time i ask, he says that there is nothing that I can do to help him yet.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

\GMP

Day 00313: Thursday, 2016 January 14

The spider continues to make slow progress, but it is still moving along. I built a simple script for listing the currently-known onions. I soon found that there was a problem with include.d that prevents my website from compiling though, so I had to turn my attention to building another wrapper class so that I could push another update.

Today's wrapper class was for use with the GD and image functions. Mostly, everything went well, but there was one function that I was not going to implement at first. Apparently, it makes use of a Windows-only extension. I thought that implementing it in my wrapper class would require building a wrapper class for some Windows-only functions, which is not at all worth my time and energy. However, it turns out that the extension already defines its own class. Instead of having to define a whole unusable wrapper class to implement this one function as a method, I only needed to write two lines of code, so I went ahead and implemented it. It felt like it might be a bit spiteful to not implement it when implementing it was so easy. There were several functions that were removed in PHP 7 though, so I left them out as code will need to migrate away from these functions anyway if they want to be future-proof.

After finishing that wrapper class, I took a look at what wrapper class I would be working on next time. I found that the next one on the list is the one for the GNU multiple precision extension. This extension is set up very poorly indeed. It already uses objects, but these objects have no methods. As the PHP manual puts it, Note: No object oriented interface is provided to manipulate GMP objects. Please use the procedural GMP API.. I started working on some initial tests to see if I would be able to extend this class when building my wrapper class, and I found some very strange results. \GMP objects have a strange ability that allows them to behave as numbers. For example, you can use them in mathematical equations. There does not seem to be a way to implement this capability without extending the \GMP class, but extending this class does not allow one to set the number that the object is to act like. Instead, the number is stuck at zero. At first, it seemed that the class was using some strange, unsettable property. This property is visible when using \var_dump(), but all attempts to change it are ineffective. However, after further testing, I found that this property seems to exist on some other layer of the object. Attempts to read this property before setting it result in an error message about the property not existing, but attempts to read the property *after* setting it result in the value you set being read back. However, \var_dump() does not show the value that is being read from and written to. Instead, it shows the value of the property overlaid from the other layer. The reason that I cannot set this value is not necessarily because it it is read-only, but because I cannot reach it. Further reading of the documentation revealed something else as well. The functions that operate on these objects, the ones that I thought should have been included as methods of the class that they operate on, do not modify the objects they work on. instead, they return new instances of the class. This alone would be implementable in my wrapper class, but the overlaid property and the capability to use instances as numbers are not something that I can duplicate. I decided not to wrap the functions simply because there was no way to do so without losing the class' special feature.

People complain about PHP due to things that they do not like about how it works on the surface, though those things do not bother me too much. Instead, it is these deeper-level things that bother me. PHP is allowed to define classes that behave differently than user-defined classes are allowed to behave. This, to me, makes the language feel a bit inconsistent. If a feature were unavailable to classes across the board, it would mean that PHP objects simply do not behave that way. Having classes with these "special" features that are unavailable to other objects makes those classes feel less like actual classes, and more like something that someone cobbled together to fill a certain need without regard to the fact that other people might have similar yet different needs.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

More specific spider output

Day 00314: Friday, 2016 January 15

I awoke this morning to find that newdawn had frozen on me. With the spider rewritten in such a way that interuptions will not do lasting harm to the database, I have not even been trying to run it in such a way that newdawn going down allows the spider to continue running, despite it running from cepo. It has been crawling a particularly large website over the past couple days though, so now it will have to start crawling that site from the beginning. I hate not seeing how close to reaching a savable state that the spider is in. I previously had to remove the progress report feature as it was not compatible with the new MySQL database, but now, the spider is back to working partially from RAM. I have added back the progress report feature, though it only reports the progress in relation to the current site, not the whole crawl.

After that, I decided to add a new feature to the cURL download-limiting class, so once more, I got to work on building another wrapper class. I went through the list of resource types and found eighteen sections of the manual that mention functions in need of wrapping. Fourteen of these sections document standard PHP extensions while four document PECL extensions. I will start with the standard extensions before working on the PECL stuff. I wanted to work on the semaphore, shared memory and IPC functions today, as I wanted to see why the functions in this section of the manual have three three different prefixes. However \ftok(), the one function in this section of the manual that had no prefix, depends on resources from the shared memory extension, so I worked on the wrapper class for those functions instead. After actually completing this tiny class, I realized that \ftok() did not really need to be implemented in any class, let alone as a method that required another class.

With that out of the way, I added a new feature to my curl_limit class to output information to the command line about the current progress of a download. The problem with this though is that it would output information whether it is used in a script that this is wanted or not, so I called it a debugging feature, made it optional, and turned it off by default. With it already being optional, I decided to make it optional in the spider too. I added a new configuration option, turned it on in the example configuration, and modified the existing output lines in the spider to respect the debug output setting. Finally, I moved the code that makes the spider work over Tor into its own constant so that it would be reusable. I made a few other minor adjustments to the spider as well, but nothing noteworthy. I have a few other somewhat important features that I want to implement in it, but I think that I will mostly put it aside for now and only fix any bugs I find in it. I want to get to work building some forum software; I have learned almost everything that the spider project had to teach me, though admittedly there is still a little left to learn from it. When the spider finishes its long crawl, perhaps that is when I will pick it back up again.

We made plans to head to Eugene on Sunday or Monday, in order to work on moving what junk we still have in Springfield into a storage unit so we can work on getting that house on the market. The plan was tentative, as if there was anything that we could do to help with Cyrus' Boy Scout project in that time, we would do that instead. However, tonight, Cyrus finally got his Boy Scout project approved! We are headed to the library, where he will be organizing some sort of organization effort.

Normally, my mother does not want to hear anything about what I am up to. I have learned to be pretty quiet and not bring things up if I can help it. However, she actually asked me today, so I took a risk, and told her about the spider. To avoid having her check back on the progress of it and seeing something disappointing, I explained that given my lack of resources (my lack of disk space), I could not support a powerful spider or build a working search engine around it. She suggested that we pick up a new hard drive at the second-hand computer store when we are in Eugene! I do not think that she understood just how much hard drive space that I think that I need. I figure that I need at least a terabyte or two. Getting a hard drive that large will not be cheap, even second hand. Now that I think on it, I would probably also need a lot more RAM and a better processor, too. I simple upgrade will not work. I would need an entire replacement machine, and it would need to be a powerful one.

I wrote back to my old school asking again how I can get my password reset. Hopefully they will actually respond this time.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Exceptions and shared memory

Day 00315: Saturday, 2016 January 16

Last night, I had a pretty bad dream in which my laptop was starting to break down physically. The metal part where the hinge attaches to the screen was bending apart. The screen was starting to detach and it was only a matter of time before it was no longer functional. Once awake though, I realized that this laptop was not my own cepo though. Cepo's shell is made of plastic, not metal. Still, what does this dream mean? Does it mean that I fear the destruction of my laptop?

The power went out this morning. By the spider's own estimate, it was over halfway finished crawling that large website that I keep trying to have it crawl, but once again, it is going to have to start over. It had crawled 37890 pages and had an estimated 19770 pages left. I really hope some day to move past this site.

Feeling stranded without Internet access, I used what power I had left in cepo's battery to work on wrapper classes. It is a good thing that I downloaded that PHP manual. Thankfully, the PHP website even offers a full-manual download option instead of requiring each page be visited and downloaded manually. Furthermore, the manual is under the CC BY 3.0 license, so I do not have to feel bad about having a copy of it on my machine. I built the functions covered by today's section of the manual into three small classes dealing with shared memory. I experimented a bit, and it seems like if modified my spider to make use of them, it should be possible to set up a script that can check on the spider's progress without keeping the spider open in my terminal window at all times. It might not be able to allow me to hook into the continuing output flow that I would have if I kept it running in my terminal window, but it would give me the freedom to allow newdawn to be put to sleep at night, or even take newdawn outside the house if desired.

As it turns out, we did not do much at the library in regards to Cyrus' project. He needed to measure some shelves, but that was all. After that, he and our mother went home, while Vanessa and I stayed to participate in the monthly coloring club. Last time, i was somewhat unprepared. It was a fun idea in theory, but we were coloring ostensibly nonfree works. This time, I asked for a blank sheet of paper and did my best to draw Floraverse's Andre from memory. I messed it up quite a bit, but it was still fun. After that, I started working on a line drawing using a ruler, but quickly realized that that was a bad idea. My underlying goal in attendance it to improve my eye hand coordination. Drawing lines using a ruler does not help me to do that.

After Vanessa and I returned home, we met back up with Cyrus and our mother and attended an earthquake lecture at the local community collage. Much of the lecture was either about things I already knew or were above my head, but one important fact did stand out: the data that these people are gathering about seismic activity is publicly accessible. The people speaking at the lecture are the Pacific Northwest Seismic Network, and their current goal seems to be to learn more about the fault line that lies just off the local coast in fairly shallow water. The lecturer also mentioned the minor earthquake in Springfield not too long ago, explaining that the reason that it was so weak is that it originated within the crust. Had it originated deep in the mantle, it would have been stronger, or if it had originated at a fault line, it would have possibly been devastating.

Whenever I write my code to throw exceptions in case of error, I have to go back to the two lists of exceptions built into PHP to try to find the best exception for the job. Furthermore, the lists do not have information with them, instead they have links to the pages that do have the information. In other words, the manual is organized, and these lists are only indexes. However, I have been thinking for quite some time that I could really use a list for quick reference. Today, I sat down to create such a list. I understand that it is helpful to define one's own exceptions when one is using them in catch blocks and only wants to catch certain types of errors, but I think that in most other cases, it is better just to use the built-in exceptions. That said, it is probably best to use the most specific available exception that applies to the situation, so I also organized the exceptions into the following list so I could better visualize the built-in exception hierarchy:

\Throwable

\Error

\ArithmeticError

\DivisionByZeroError

\AssertionError
\ParseError
\TypeError

\Exception

\ErrorException
\LogicException

\BadFunctionCallException

\BadMethodCallException

\DomainException
\InvalidArgumentException
\LengthException
\OutOfRangeException

\RuntimeException

\OutOfBoundsException
\OverflowException
\RangeException
\UnderflowException
\UnexpectedValueException

It is worth noting that the \Throwable interface and everything in the \Error branch of the tree are only available in PHP 7, not in PHP5. It seems that PHP 7 is built to be more object-oriented than PHP 5, so these added exceptions are available for internal use, allowing the language to throw exceptions instead of raising errors. It sounds like if these built-in exceptions are not caught, the regular error handler will be called, but hopefully the exception's backtrace will be kept intact when this happens and will be output with the error message.

Before going to bed, our mother gave Vanessa, Cyrus, and I a strange quiz that made me nervous. Much of it was about how we feel about things, but with her being the type to overreact about things and in many ways be intolerant, I did feel the need to lie in my answers. I talked to Cyrus later, and is seems that he had come to a similar conclusion when he had assessed the situation. I did not get a chance to speak with Vanessa about it, but my guess is that she reached the same conclusion that we did and took the same precautionary measures.

This winter, I was pretty cold, as most of the blankets that we have are made from animal products, so I refused to use them. At least, that is what I thought at the time. I had thought that fleece was synthetic, but someone told me that it was an animal product. Being busy, I never looked into it, but the other day, someone else told me that fleece is made of polyester! I looked into it today, and it turns out that the cloth that people typically call "fleece" is actually called polar fleece. This fabric is also known as "polar wool", "vega wool", and "velo wools", but despite its animal-sounding names, it is made of polyethylene terephthalate, a type of polyester. Fleece is just plastic! Had I actually done research when I was told that it was an animal product, I could have been warm this winter.

It seems that wowaname's server is back up! That must be a relief for her. When my server is down, I feel stranded, even if my laptop is still online. I assume that she feels similarly.

It sounds like the plan to go to Eugene and Springfield tomorrow or the next day may still happen. If this does happen before the spider finishes crawling the huge website that it is working with, it will once again have to be interrupted. It will have to begin its progress from scratch yet again. The alternative is to leave newdawn in Coos Bay, but that would mean potentially being unable to write a journal entry or two while events are still fresh in my mind.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Too many resource handles; time to work on the spider again

Day 00316: Sunday, 2016 January 17

Today, I was thinking today about how the \gnupg_*() functions that I use to sign pages on this site use resource handles, but are not listed on the list of resources and the functions that use them. I know that several such resource types exist, but what are the chances that I will happen to run across them all? Furthermore, if I do not run across them all, I would only be wrapping the ones that I happen to find out about, which would likely be the ones that are of some use to me personally. How arbitrary would that be? With that in mind, I decided to grep the manual. The output was enormous. While most likely not every file listed is actually a function that I need to wrap, most of those hits are probably actually functions that I need to work with. It looks like my little resource-wrapping project is far from over. I admittedly did have to tweak my grep input a bit to rule out a bunch of false positives though. The first time I used grep, it showed me at least four pages out of every manual section, even if that section did not cover functions that were in need of resource handles.

Among the grep results, I found an idiotically-built under-documented class: \MysqlndUhConnection. It does not seem to actually produce make a database connection and produce the resource handle that it needs upon instantiation. Because of this, all of its methods aside from __construct() either require a resource handle as one of their arguments. What is even the point in having this be a class to begin with? It is essentially procedural code. The manual does not seem to mention what this class is used for, though the example code uses custom subclasses of this class instead of using this class directly. The custom subclasses have the same issue as their parent class though. While it is possible for a child class to fix the problems by containing a resource as a property, this is not done in the examples. As it turns out, this class is not meant to instantiate objects that will be used by the programmer directly. Instead, they are passed into the \mysqlnd_uh_set_connection_proxy() function. The reason that the methods take the handles as arguments is that \mysqlnd_uh_set_connection_proxy() causes the object to act on any resource handle passed to certain functions and multiple handles may be used in a script. This class is meant to be extended by the programmer to hook into the functions a bit. It really had me confused and frustrated when I first read about this class, but now that I understand better, I know that there is nothing wrong with this class. There is likewise no need to extend this class and encapsulate a resource, as this class is not built for that type of functionality. It would have been nice if the class' main documentation page actually had this information though. Instead, no usage information is given there.

I also ran across an under-documented method that asks for an unspecified type of resource: \SWFMovie::saveToFile(). I suspect that the resource handle to use is a file pointer, so I might build this into my f class. Next, I found the \bcompiler_*() functions, but I do not like them at all. According to the introduction, these functions are for use in encoding proprietary PHP applications to avoid having to release the source code for those applications. The other use it mentions is to compile PHP code so that the PHP executable for Windows is not needed. It looks to me that this extension if for use in environments without package mangers and without source code access. Horrified, I decided not to wrap these functions at all. I will just ignore them and pretend that they do not exist. Another anomaly I ran across rested with the \mqseries_*() functions. The functions used to generate resource handles spit three or four of them out at a time, passing those resource handles out by reference. It took a few times of reading over this section to figure out where to even get the required resource handles from and I still do not know how the resources are used yet. Now that I know where they come from though, I will set those functions aside for now.

After a while, I stopped sorting the grep output. There are so many resource types in need of being wrapped in classes and if I continue on this wrapper project, most of include.d will consist of only wrapper classes. This is not the vision that I have for my PHP function/class/constant library. When I thought there were far less resource types, I accepted the fact that there would be more wrapper classes than other classes for the time being, but I figured that the rest of the library would catch up soon enough. Without finishing sorting grep's output, I already count forty-six wrapper classes that I have not completed in addition to twenty-one wrapper classes that I have already completed and an unknown number of wrapper classes that I have yet to sort out of the grep output. There will likely be over eighty wrapper classes to build in total, and that is just too many until I manage to pack more functional code into include.d. For now, I will abandon my wrapper class project, aside to add in the wrapper classes that I am actually going to use, such as the one for the gnupg_*() functions. I will attempt to push harder on my other projects in an effort to drive my development of include.d code. I will push ahead in my development of the onion space spider before working on the Web forum I had planned as well. It will be nice to have that in a more presentable state. I might still work on wrapper classes when I have nothing at all better to do, or use them to drive my other work forward by telling myself that if I do not get to work on some other project, I will force myself to work on boring wrapper classes instead.

I tried to detach my terminal session from the running spider, but I ended up failing and killing the spider. I really hope that the site's webmaster does not think that my spider's repeated crawls are an attempt at a DDoS attack. This time, I ran it with nohup on the command line. This caused the output to not show up on the command line, but perhaps that is for the best. The output is being redirected to a file, so I can read it whenever I log back into cepo. I also found though that if I delete the logging file, it is not created again with new output. Instead, further output seems to be lost.

It seems that I have lost the headphone jack cover for my mobile case. I have been unable to locate it for several days. Speaking of my mobile, I have shut my Replicant down for the time being. My ties to my current carrier are coming to an end, so I have switched the SIM card over to the wimpy Android that is locked to their service. In a few days, after having the device on their service for a while, I will try to get the thing unlocked, then switch back to the Replicant if successful.

We did not end up heading to Eugene and Springfield today, but we are headed out early tomorrow.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Removing wrapper classes

Day 00317: Monday, 2016 January 18

I have decided to not only halt progress on my wrapper classes, but to backtrack. Simply put, I do not know which functions are worth wrapping in many cases, as I do not know which functions are even worth using. I do not need include.d to be cluttered with junk code. With that in mind, I am removing any wrapper class that I have never actually used, ass well as my dir wrapper class, which I feel is made obsolete by the built-in \scandir() function.

I did not have much time this morning before leaving for Springfield, but I did start putting together a function to help me debug include.d. All the function really did was load all of include.d's functions, classes, and constants, which meant that any syntax errors would become immediately visible. However, on the way to Springfield, I decided to put together a battery of tests for the actual output of these functions and classes. Soon after, I decided that my initial function was kind of arbitrary as a function, and really belonged as part of the test code, so I downgraded my plans for the function itself. It would instead be just a set of loops in the test code and it would rely on a constant within include.d to know where include.d was so it could be recursed. By adding const _DIR_ = __DIR__; to include.d's constants file, I would have a way to tell the test suite where include.d's files were. By the end of the day though, I had realized that the test suite did not need include.d to be modified in any way. stream_resolve_include_path('st/y') would tell my test suite exactly where to find my functions and classes so that they all can be loaded. I feel that this is the cleanest way to make it work, as it does not rely on adding stupid hacks to include.d. I will of course still add individual test cases for each function and class, but this will mean that I will not have to remember to individually require() each of my functions.

We did not get as much work done in Springfield as we wanted to, nor are we ready to rent that storage unit. Still, the planning that i was able to make for my test suite while working made the day worthwhile for me.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Unicorns Get More Bacon

Day 00318: Tuesday, 2016 January 19

I thought that my old school still has not written back to me about resetting my password, but their live chat option is now actually functioning. I was able to speak with someone that changed the email address on my account to my current email address, but password resetting still does not work. He recommended that I contact a different section of the support team, so I have now sent an email to them. Hopefully they will actually respond. However, later in the day, I started trying to retame my inbox. I have allowed myself to get quite behind in processing email. While it is true that some support departments have not been responding to me, it turns out that one section of the school's support team did get back to me. Embarassingly, they got back to me as early as the first of this month. They wanted some personal information in order to verify that I am the real account holder, so now that i have sent that, hopefully I should be able to get back into my account soon.

My onion spider has crashed again. It turns out that there was an error both in the spider itself and in include.d. The error in the spider causes it to neglect to check the output of merge_uris(). merge_uris() outputs a string if \parse_url() is able to handle the relative URI passed to merge_uris(), but if \parse_url() outputs a boolean false, so does merge_uris(). The spider assumes that output will be a string, even though merge_uris() is explicitly programmed to sometimes output false. The error in merge_uris() caused it to output a boolean false if \parse_url() outputs an empty array, which it apparently does when given the string "#", which appears as the target of a hyperlink on the page that my spider choked on. Thankfully, the hyperlink that my spider choked on was not on the huge website that it has been stuck repeatedly crawling over the past week or so. It has finished crawling that website, so it will now leave that website alone for at least a month. I fixed the bug in include.d, but I felt that the bug in the spider was too useful for the time being to fix yet. I do not know of any situation in which \parse_url() actually returns a boolean false, so until the spider or I run into such a case, the bug in the spider helps be debug include.d.

Marc With a C has a new album available for prerelease order: Unicorns Get More Bacon. I cannot say that I like the title of the album, but I usually like his music, and he said that early adopters might get an unspecified bonus, so I tried to order the album. After all, I will probably buy it later anyway. However, PayPal is once again being a pain and refusing to process my payment. Once more, I have begun pestering PayPal support about their issues publicly on Twitter. Trying again later, the payment went through, though I am curious as to how PayPal will respond to my complaint. Strangely, the PayPal website said that it was only charging me $10 USD instead of $13 USD at first, but then it corrected itself to $ USD. After placing the order, Bandcamp instantly added the album to my collection, but then Marc gave me a code to download it early, and using the code added it to my collection a second time, so I now have two of it, just like I have two of Professor Shyguy's Fragmentation.

While writing the part of my debugging code that loads all of include.d's classes, functions, and constants, I found an oddity in the \class_exists() function. In the past, it returned true if the class name checked corresponded to an existing regular class or an interface, but was later modified to only return true if the class name checked corresponds to a non-interface class and a new \interface_exists() function was added to check for the existence of an interface. What was even the point of that? Interfaces and non-interface classes exist within the same name space. There is no need to check a different name space, so there is no need for a second function to check it. When traits were added, a new \trait_exists() function was added, and \class_exists() only returns true if the class name corresponds to an existing, non-trait, non-interface class. As best as I can figure, as all of these things are in the same name space, these functions first check to see if the name is being used, then check to see what type of class is using it. But what if we just want to know if the name is in use? There seems to be quite literally no function that meets this basic need, so we have to instead check the output of all three functions. That means that the name is checked for use three times when we only need to know about one name!

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

The \gnupg class

Day 00319: Wednesday, 2016 January 20

My old school got back to me, so now I can get into my old account. I went through my account to update my email address and remove the telephone number from the account, however, it seems that they do not even allow one to update one's telephone number. I had forgotten about that. Back when I attended that school, I had changed my telephone number partway through, but I had been unable to update my telephone number on the account. Their system is pretty stupid, really. I had also forgotten how slow their website is. It majorly slows down the whole Web browser. In any case, I will walk into the local community college tomorrow, fill out their paperwork, and pay their fee. Once home from there, I will pay my old school to send the community college a copy of my transcript.

It seems that Marc With a C is having troubles with PayPal lately. I am not the only one that PayPal torments! For Marc though, PayPal is charging strange amounts for shipping if his customers order on a mobile device. Apparently, PayPal is charging some mobile users $20 USD for shipping. PayPal is horrid. I really hope that Bandcamp starts offering a non-PayPal method of payment. If and when they add a second payment option, I will hopefully be able to quit using PayPal's services forever.

I had a chat with a representative of my carrier about getting my carrier-provided device unlocked today. I do not typically use that device, as it is too locked down for daily use, but it is useful for experimentation. The carrier refused to unlock the device, stating that I needed to wait one more month. In all honestly, I was in fact trying to get it unlocked a month early. With some carefully-chosen words though, I managed to get the representative to agree to unlock my device a single day early. She said that she made a note of that on my account, so if I contact support a day early, I can get it unlocked.

I looked into what is necessary to implement Sitemap support in my spider. As it turns out, not a whole lot is needed. The Sitemap protocol defines two types of XML files, Sitemaps and Sitemap indexes. Both of these use <loc/> tags to tell a crawler about other files on the website. All I had to do was copy the code that handles <a/> tags and modify it slightly to use <loc/> tags instead. My implementation causes the spider to look for both <a/> tags and <loc/> tags on both webpages and Sitemaps alike, but that should be fine. In theory, Sitemaps do not contain <a/> tags and webpages do not contain <loc/> tags. In practice, most Web developers fail to adhere to standards, but I am building the spider to accept whatever input that it is able to understand. As much as I value standards, I am not going to try to penalize sites for not adhering to them.

I finished processing my email. I need to stop allowing myself to fall behind.

Cyrus told our mother that he is giving up on his Boy Scout project. This really set her off. She told Cyrus off for quite a while. She said that Cyrus aught to go live with our father, but was also pressuring him to cut all ties with our father. She says that she is not kicking him out, though he thought that she was at first. Partway through telling off Cyrus, she offered to allow me to go to Portland with Alyssa for a bit, but given the context, it feels like a trap to me. Just before, she was claiming that we do not care about her. I need to tread carefully. Most likely, the "correct" option is to not go.

I set up the wrapper class for the gnupg_*() functions, as I actually do use those function. I must say though that it is nice not having to build wrapper classes that I do not use though. However, after building this class, PHP started claiming that the \gnupg_init() function does not exist. Strangely enough, whenever my class is defined, the function does not seem to exist, but whenever my class does not exist, the function does. Trying several things, I eventually moved my class into the root namespace for more testing, and I found that I could not "redeclare" the \gnupg class. It turns out that the GNU Privacy Guard extension defines its own undocumented class! This still does not explain the errors about the function "not existing", but I deleted my class and now everything works as expected. I started to post a note in the PHP documentation, but after reading the page that they ask all users to read before posting, I found that they prefer that such things not be posted as notes. Instead, they want bug reports filed, so I filed a bug report instead.

Our cat has been a bit sluggish lately, and we can tell that she is not feeling well. We had assumed that she is simply a bit sick and will recover, but my mother has proposed another theory: perhaps she is dying. She has gotten old, and she might not have much time left. Even if she is not quite at death's door, older cats start to lose their energy and become more sedentary. According to Wikipedia, cats tend to live about twelve to fifteen years, and she is twelve years old. Another possibility is that she is in fact just sick, but that she picked up the disease because we visited that cat shelter and brought something home. We all tried to wash up thoroughly, before going anywhere near her, but one of us may not have washed up as well as we should have. As odd as it is to say, I think that I will be fine if the cat passes away. I know that everything dies, and unlike most people, I feel that when something dies, everything that they once were is gone. I do not mean this in just a souls-are-a-myth way, but also that it does not matter how long you live if you still have to die. Death, to me, causes life to have no value. I do want the cat to continue living and get better because I like her and like having her around, but more than that, I want her to get continue living and get better because I think that the other members of the family will have less guilt on their minds that way. There will be less chance of them thinking that perhaps they killed the cat and that things would be different if they had only made sure to clean themselves more thoroughly. I suppose that makes me a bit cold, but I do not know any other way to feel; death is unavoidable.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Buĉita

Day 00320: Thursday, 2016 January 21

Late last night, I started making adjustments to the organization scheme of my music files to better integrate the music I bought on Professor Shyguy's USB drive. This morning, I found that my Web spider keeps dying without an error message, but due to the fact that I had already started reorganizing files, I was not able to put much time into debugging. I hate having my files in an awkward state between two organizations schemes, as it makes my files practically unusable. I tried running the spider again a couple more times, but it always ended up terminating itself without any error messages from my code or from PHP. I finally tried running the spider directly instead of running it through nohup, and when the spider got to the file in onion space that always caused it to terminate, the command line presented a single-word message: "Buĉita", which Wiktionary says is the past tense form of the Esperanto word meaning to slaughter. Clearly, bash was simply telling me that the process had been killed. Between the fact that I needed to finish organizing files and the fact that I had other errands to run today, I was unable to spend any more time debugging. Tomorrow, if I have time, I will add some line-by-line output to the spider to find the exact like that is choking on that file.

When I was at the local community college the other day, I was told that I could fill out their application for enrollment either online or in person. I was also told that either way, I could pay in-person if I wanted to. To fill out the application online but pay in-person, I was told to fill out the application first, then come in to pay and tell the teller that I had filled out the application online. I had planned to fill out the application in person when paying, but today before I left for the school, I had a passing thought: If I tried to fill out the form online but the form would not allow me to submit without including a telephone number, I would have a chance to bring it up with the teller when I went in in hopes of getting that fixed. People have a right to not have telephone service if they do not want it, without stupid barriers such as forms not allowing submission, so if I can help move things in the right direction, I should do that. With that in mind, I filled out the form online, but much to my surprise, the telephone number was optional. The section for providing an emergency contact also allowed the telephone number field to remain blank, so I provided only an email address. However, on completion of the form, no option to postpone payment was given. The only option was to pay by credit card online. I hit the "cancel" link, which I thought would cancel the entire form submission, but that caused the website to say that the form was submitted successfully. I figured that once I got to the school, they would know whether or not the form actually had submitted my information, so I headed out.

I stopped at Banner Bank to withdraw the money that I needed to pay the school, and as usual, I withdrew it in one-dollar bills. The teller asked if that helped me make my money last longer, so I explained that I do it because I stamp my money. More bills means more stamps. Much to my dismay, the teller explained that Banner Bank sends stamped money back to the government to be destroyed, including money stamped with the common "where is George" stamps. This is not going to work well for me. I might switch banks when I get a chance.

Because I was already in the area, I also payed my mobile bill. The cashier offered to send me a receipt by email, so I happily handed over my email address. However, the system would not accept my email address, likely either because my email address does not end in ".com" or because of the single-character label in the domain. Some system-builders use such idiotic methods of validating an email address.

Once at the local community college, I was informed that they do not actually have any way to know if my information was sent to them. Until I paid the fee, there was no chance of anyone looking for my information, and after paying the fee, I have to wait until a particular employee with more access to the system to take a look. They said that I should receive a letter of approval by postal mail in about a week. If I do not, I will walk back in and see what they have to say about it.

After returning home, I got to work ordering transcripts from my old school. Their site was having issues though, so I tried to get help from one of their live chat representatives. However, the representative refused to help me because he did not like my operating system. But this was a website. What operating system I use makes no difference! I tried back a little later though, and someone had fixed the website.

Cyrus' Boy Scout project has now been approved, and it seems that he is now un-giving up, at least for now. He has little time left, but we will be working on organizing media at the local library tomorrow.

Marc has shipped my order of Unicorns Get More Bacon, so I will be keeping an eye out for that. If the United States Postal Service did not maliciously discriminate against Tor users, I would be able to track the order, but unfortunately, they do. I am curious to see what bonus he threw in, but being paranoid, I fear that he did not throw it in as I chose a CD instead of a vinyl record. His message was not specific though. It says Order a physical edition of the album and get a download of the whole record sent to your email box (if it's different from the email associated with your PayPal account, PLEASE SPECIFY WHERE YOU WANT THE DOWNLOAD TO BE SENT!) within 24 hours! You might end up with a bonus item, because I'm pretty good at taking care of early adopters. My track record speaks for itself. Thank you, and please tell everyone you know about this album! If I were not so paranoid, I would know very well that he said "physical", not "vinyl". I would also know that Marc is the kind of person that does things just to make fans happy. I am worrying over nothing, but still, I must worry. Even if I get no bonus though, the music I already have from this purchase is surely worth it. I have only heard the opening track, but the digital download did come with eleven other tracks that I can listen to when I get the chance.

Speaking of music, I finished organizing my music files, but I used the mv command from the shell a few times without thinking, and some of my files have the same names, just in different directories. I may have overwritten some of my files. At some point, I am going to need to delete all the files from my music library and copy my ZIP files back out of my archive. Re-extracting them, I can be sure that I have not lost anything. I might change my naming scheme a bit too to make future reorganizing easier. If none of my music files have the same name, I can simply drag and drop them, or even use mv without worry.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Is the oom-killer the problem?

Day 00321: Friday, 2016 January 22

I tracked down the issue with the spider. The \xml_parse_into_struct() function is supposed to return 0 on failure and 1 on success, but instead, the script simply terminates upon calling that function. Someone on IRC explained that the likely cause was oom-killer, some sort of daemon that kills processes that take too much memory. They also explained that when parsing data, three to five times the file's size is needed in RAM. However, while this explanation seems exceedingly likely, I cannot find any trace of this happening in the logs. Additionally, when I set the file download size limit to four megabytes, the spider still ended up dead. Because Web servers can lie about file content types, I want to solve this issue without relying on Content-Type headers, though after I have done so, I want to additionally start taking Content-Type headers into account. I think that by modifying my curl_limit class, I can check the Content-Type header before the download has finished. I think that I want to make the class a bit more complex, both giving it the option to abort a download based on the Content-Type header and giving it a way to communicate error messages (such as the fact that it had to abort a download and why) to other parts of a script that uses it. The name curl_limit will either need to be changed or it will become a artifact title.

I spent most of the day sorting VHS cassettes at the local library in an effort to help Cyrus with his Boy Scout project. We took any cassette off the shelf if it had not been checked out in over a year so that they can be removed from the inventory and sold. It was mostly uneventful, though the librarian was very happy with our work. We have not finished though, so we will be back in tomorrow.

Vivian will be coming to town tonight, though she had not arrived yet at the time that I had written my weblog entry. She will also be helping with the Boy Scout project to move progress along.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Document modifications

On 2018-01-16, my sister, Vivian, requested that I replace all instances of her legal name in my journal with the name "Vivian". She also asked that the name of the organisation she works for be redacted. This page was modified to fulfil that request.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

\CURLOPT_NOPROGRESS, \curl_getinfo(), and \parse_url()

Day 00322: Saturday, 2016 January 23

I did a bit of searching, and I found that there is a bug in how \xml_parse_into_struct() handles deeply-nested tags. According to the Red Hat bug report, this bug is capable of crashing a script. Due to the fact that the file that crashes the spider not being an actual XML file, I have no idea how it is being interpreted. The spider only sends it to that function because it has no way to know if the file is an XML/HTML file, so it sends all files through that function. After several more hours of debugging though, I finally found a problem in my spider itself that is making this problem worse: the progress function that I set is not being called! I removed a line that set the \CURLOPT_NOPROGRESS option to false, as I thought that it was leftover code that was not needed. The PHP manual says that \CURLOPT_NOPROGRESS should only be used for debugging, but this is a lie! If \CURLOPT_NOPROGRESS is not set to false, the progress function will never be called. The original instructions for setting up a file size limit were very helpful, as was the fact that my limiting function was set to generate output, though not output was being generated. Once I had the problem fixed though, too much output was being generated, ,so I had to disable that feature. I set up a new setting to re-enable it in the configuration file though. It seems that my file size limit might have been too high though, so I turned it down to eight megabytes. I am unsure if this file size is low enough to prevent future problems with non-XML files or if the problem is only prevented for now because the file that triggered the error this particular time is larger than this limit.

I looked further into the \curl_getinfo() function, but it seems that it is not suitable for use in the spider. If a single cURL handle is used for multiple file transfers, the output of this function gets a bit muddled. Specifically, if this file is called multiple times, any value that the function returned on a previous call will be called again, unless that value is overridden by a new value. That means that if the function is not yet able to retrieve information on the current download when called from within my curl_limit class, it will reuse the last-known value, which could be from a different download. I theorize that if I modified the curl_limit class to abort selected downloads based on the Content-Type header, files that the spider attempts to retrieve after the aborted download will also be potentially aborted, as curl_limit objects seem to get called several times before the server actually returns data, so the headers are not yet available.

On the topic of optimization of include.d code, I realized today that my CURLOPT_TOR constant has an issue. It relies on the \CURL* constants, which unless the cURL extension is installed and loaded, do not exist. This constant is only useful when the cURL extension is loaded, but it is defined any time any constant in the name space is needed.

We went out to some dunes to do some cooking on the trail, as Cyrus had to do that today to meet one of his Boy Scout requirements. Unfortunately, he forgot to bring both the metal screen to put over the fire and the pot to cook in, so we had to go back home to get them, using up some of what little time we have. Upon returning to the dunes, we gathered firewood and sap to build a fire and cook a meal. We then rushed back into town so that Cyrus could meet up with one of his counselors and get some of his requirements signed off on.

While he was meeting with the counsellor, Vivian gave me a calendar and newspaper from the volunteer organization that she works with to look over. Today was hectic, so I was unable to look them over today, but hopefully they will give me a better idea of what she does.

Upon returning home, Cyrus went over a few quick things with us in order to pass off more requirements. We discussed emergency situations and what to do in them, put together an emergency backpack, then discussed the family finances. After that, we were off to the local public library to finish our work there. We finished pruning the analog electronic media (VHS cassettes and audio cassettes), then finished moving them all over to a single section to condense them. We cleaned off the dust on the freed shelves, reconfigured the shelves to have different spacing, and spread the digital electronic media out to allow room for collection growth.

Once home from the library, Cyrus worked more on his Boy Scout requirements on his own. For me, it was time to once again debug the spider. It was again choking of a supposedly-empty URI due to that bug that I intentionally did not fix the other day. This time, however, my code was just fine; I had not gotten a blank URI due to an error in my code. I tracked down the hyperlink that caused the issue, and it was pointed at the URI "#fn:1". I immediately saw the problem: \parse_url() was seeing the colon and getting confused. To test my theory, I called \parse_url() directly and passed in the troublesome URI fragment, and sure enough, the function returned falls. The next step was clear. I needed to find out whether the URI fragment is valid. If the formatting is valid, I would know that \parse_url() is broken and I need to rewrite merge_uris() to use some other method or breaking URIs into their components. On the other hand, if that syntax is invalid, this was not a problem in \parse_url(). Instead of rewriting merge_uris(), I needed to simply fix the bug in the spider.

As it turns out, that URI fragment is completely valid. I that same document, an example regular expression that parses a URI is present in the document, though the RFCs are not under a free license. Luckily, someone that prefers to remain unmentioned helped me find a document saying that IETF document code components are covered by the Modified BSD license. I should be able to construct a working function tomorrow if I have time.

In the end, Cyrus was unable to meet his project deadline of midnight tonight. However, it seems that he has been granted a short extension, allowing him to finish up by nine tomorrow.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Document modifications

On 2018-01-16, my sister, Vivian, requested that I replace all instances of her legal name in my journal with the name "Vivian". She also asked that the name of the organisation she works for be redacted. This page was modified to fulfil that request.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Walking in tomorrow to try again to get health care

Day 00324: Monday, 2016 January 25

This morning, I looked into government-sponsored health care again, as they still have not gotten back to me. I sent in my application last month, and now this month is almost over. It seems that there are places that I can go to get help in person. I was planning to walk in today, but I took too long getting ready. The place that can help is several hours away from home and I foolishly wanted to set up my music library on my mobile before leaving. I will have to go in tomorrow instead.

After deciding on a new file organization scheme for my music library, I knew that I would either have to find a way to use Ex Falso's conditional syntax more effectively or I would need to do a lot of the sorting by hand. I found a page in the Quod Libet manual explaining that Ex Falso's conditionals do not only have an if syntax, but also an optional else syntax, which is exactly what I needed. My new file-renaming string is ~/Muziko/\\NEW\\/<albumartist|<albumartist>|\\>/<albumartist>\\<album>/<title|<albumartist>\\<album>\\<title>|<title>>.

Instead of going downtown, I spent most of the day working with regular expressions. After further reading of RFC 3986, I decided that I do in fact want to build my URI parser to be strict. Names are very important to me, especially globally-unique names, and in many ways, that is what URIs are. I do not want to support invalid names. Once I had that decided, I thought that I could modify the regular expression listed in RFC 3986, both combining it with another regular expression that I built today and giving it new features that would enforce validity and break the "authority" component down into its "userdata", "host", and "port" components. However, once I got to the part about enforcing path validity, I saw that my approach would not only produce an ugly and unreadable regular expression, it would also be highly difficult. My regular expression would need to branch in a confusing way near the beginning, due to the fact that the characters that are allowed to make up the beginning of a path heavily depend on the presence, or lack of presence, of the authority and scheme components. There are five different regular expressions that can determine the validity of a path based on this presence or lack of presence, and they would need to somehow bee hooked into the parts of the main expression that matches the scheme and authority. Such a simple view does not work. I will need a multi-step approach after all, so most of the code I wrote today is no good. My new understanding of the situation should help me write something very usable though.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Learning about the ircs: URI scheme

Day 00325: Tuesday, 2016 January 26

I have been dealing with an ear infection over the past few days, and it has been worrying me quite a bit. I have been told that ear infections require treatment. I did some research online, and the results backed up my fear. They all said that antibiotics are required, but the health insurance people still have not gotten back to me. I decided to rephrase my search. Instead of asking what needs to be done about ear infections, I asked about what happens if ear infections are not treated. Mostly, the results were much more reassuring. As it turns out, medical professionals often say to wait out ear infections instead of prescribing antibiotics in an effort to avoid having the bacteria build up a resistance to the antibiotics. If I went to see a doctor, there is a good chance that I would not be prescribed anything anyway. Furthermore, ear infections appear to be common right after having caught a cold, and I have just gotten over one. The bacteria in my ear is likely just common cold bacteria and is likely nothing more than annoying. I also learned about the anatomy of the ear and why I do not seem to be able to drain the liquid I feel in there; it is behind the ear drum. There is a drainage tube leading from the liquid chamber behind the ear drum to the throat, but when this tube becomes swollen, liquid cannot drain and it becomes a cesspool. In some cases, this buildup can lead to a rupture of the ear drum. This sounds painful, but according to what the Internet said, it actually brings relief to the pain, as the liquid can drain, then the ear drum heals later. This makes a lot more sense, as it seems like it would have been quite difficult for the human species to survive before medication existed if something as small as an ear infection was likely to be highly hazardous. Evolution would have favored those that could survive with minimal damage. On the other hand, there was some worrying news too. One site said that there is an eighty percent chance that an ear infection will clear up without complications. Of course, I read that as there being a twenty percent chance of complications. I find that percentage to be alarmingly high! Another site mentioned that sometimes, an ear infection can lead to a brain infection, which would not be good news at all.

Though I am feeling under the weather, it seems that our cat is feeling a lot better. She has been much more active and much less mopey lately.

I headed out to get help with the government health insurance application in-person, fearing that my mailed-in application had been silently ignored. I made it most of the way to the building of the company that the government health care website said could help with little difficulty, but the street addresses on that street are screwy. I got to one spot in which the addresses went down in both directions. Confused, I had to stop and ask for directions. Once I got there, I found that the official government health care website had lied. I had walked out past the edge of the far end of town for nothing. These people were not able to help. The trip was not a complete bust though, I suppose. The man there did have some useful information. First, he explained that when he applied for coverage, it took two months for them to respond, and that was during their off season. I only applied a little over a month ago, an now is their busy season. Second, there is a clinic a lot closer to my home that can help with the application. I still want to try submitting in person, just to be safe.

By altering my route a bit, I was able to pass by very close to the clinic on the way home, so I made a slight detour and stopped by the clinic. They were unable to help with the application right away, but they had me register with the clinic and set up an appointment for Monday. Monday is the day after the application is due though, so I do not know how helpful that will be. Hopefully either the mailed-in application or the day-late application will be accepted though.

I found a flaw in the regular expression mentioned in RFC 3986. This regular expression works perfectly if the URI that is being parsed is known to be valid, but I malformed URIs with blank schemes will cause the scheme's delimiter, the colon, to be interpreted as the authority and causes the double slash delimitor and the authority to be interpreted as part of the path. I built my own regular expression to fix this issue, and my new regular expression additionally parses the userdata, host, and port out of the authority component. My new parse_uri() function will now return a similar array as PHP's \parse_url() function, but with a few key differences. First and formost, \parse_url()'s documentation says that it does not work on general URIs and does not work on relative URIs. However, parse_uri() is designed explicitly to work with all URIs that conform to the general syntax, including relative URIs. Second, parse_uri() will by default call another function, normalize_uri(). This function will perform any normalizations needed, and also throw an exception if a URI's components are invalid. To deal with invalid URIs, parse_uri() can be told with an argument to avoid normalization. Last, and least importantly, parse_uri() does not have "user" and "pass" keys in its returned array. Instead, it has a unified "userinfo" key, as the general URI syntax does not split up the userinfo into user and password information. This separation is left for specific URI schemes to implement in whatever way they decide to.

Having learned more about URIs, I now know that the default port used by a URI with no explicitly-set port is not set by the port registry. Instead, the default port for a URI is defined by the scheme's definition. If I am going to set up the function to normalize URIs, I am going to need to know the port numbers associated with each scheme, so I looked up the scheme registry. I was curious about the defined default for the ircs: and irc: schemes, as many ports are used for both protocols. It turns out that the ircs: scheme uses the official IRCS port assigned by IANA as its default, but the irc: scheme uses one of the newer alternative ports allowed by IANA. This seems inconsistent to me. More importantly though, it means that I need to fix all the links to IRC networks in my weblog. I assumed port 6697 as the default, but port 994 is the real default, so I need to correct my hyperlinks to explicitly specify a port.

It also seems that the fragment of a URI is delimited by the pound symbol, but cannot contain pound symbols. This lead to more questions for me in regards to the ircs: scheme. First, that means when using the URI ircs://example.com/#channel, it should be interpreted as having a fragment of channel, which as it does not contain the pound symbol, is not a complete channel name. Second, the URI ircs://example.com/#channel,#otherchannel should be invalid, as it has two pound symbols. This also means that links to channels not beginning in a pound symbol, while rare, will be interpreted as path data, while channels beginning in a pound symbol will be interpreted as the presence of a fragment, as well as the data contained in the fragment. I found several interesting things though. First, the syntax used to link to multiple channels using a single URI is invalid. The official syntax simply does not work that way. Second, the ircs: and irc: schemes treat unencoded pound signs as equivalent to encoded pound signs. This means that a general-purpose URI parser will interpret channel names as part of the path or as the beginning of the fragment depending on if the pound sign is encoded or not, but an ircs:/irc: scheme-specific parser will not. I do not anticipate that this will cause issues for my parser though, as long as URIs still conform to the ircs:/irc: scheme specification, as only one channel name is allowed per URI, so only one pound sign, if any, should be present. Invalid URIs that try to point to multiple channels might cause issues though. Another interesting feature is that it is possible to link to users instead of channels. One thing that I do not like about this scheme though is that instead of an IP address or domain name, you can also link to an unregistered pet name. As long as everyone is using the same pet name list, that works, but using domain names is a much more reliable option.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Default port numbers

Day 00326: Wednesday, 2016 January 27

My CD from Marc With a C came in the mail today. The large envelope read DO NOT BEND!!! in full capital letters and underlines, but the postal service had managed to let it get bent anyway, damaging the contents. As it turns out, I did not need to order the vinyl version of the album to get the bonus for early adopters that had been hinted at, but I would need a record player to make use of the bonus. It is a two-song forty-five RPM vinyl record. Though the postal service had damaged the record's sheath, I found the record to be quite amusing. I do not recognize either of the songs on the record, but at some point when I have more time, I might look them up.

I received the letter from the local community college saying that I have been accepted. The school told me to hold off a bit before asking for an appointment to review my credits and decide what courses I need to take, but I forget how long that they said that I should wait. I will be in the area on Monday as the clinic is very close to there, so I will probably drop by then, despite it probably being earlier than they wanted. If they have a problem with it, they can simply tell me again what the best date for me to drop by is. I will likely only be able to schedule a meeting anyway, so scheduling early sounds like a good thing.

As the generic URI normalization process includes removing the port from the URI if it matches the scheme-specific default port, I need a list of default ports on hand just to perform generic URI normalization. I decided to implement the list of URI scheme default port numbers as a constant, but I quickly found that the constant's array was huge. I think that separating constants into their own files might be a better option than I had originally thought. In the past, constants could not hold arrays and holding a single value in each file seems like a waste. With arrays though, like values, or rather, values related to the same topic, can be implemented as arrays instead of scalar values. Not only does this allow single-constant files to make more sense, it also provides a much better grouping mechanism for related information that the previously-used constant name prefixes.

I found a couple interesting schemes today. The first is the adiumxtra scheme. No real information is available about how it works, but my best guess when looking at their website is that it works exactly like the HTTP scheme, but because it is technically a different scheme, Adium is able to set itself as the handler of URIs using it, so hyperlinks can be set up that facilitate easy installation of plugins. I would try some experimenting, but Adium is only available for OS X. Another interesting scheme that I ran across is the apt scheme. Allegedly, this allows one to link to a package in a Debian repository. It does not seem to work on my machine, but it is worth using whenever I talk about Debian packages.

On the topic of URIs, I have something that I should really get out there. A while ago, I said that HTTPS and HTTP URIs that lack a path are technically invalid. By that, I meant that https://example.com is an invalid URI, as it did not even include the / path. However, a few days ago, I found new information. That URI, as well as other HTTPS and HTTP URIs that lack a trailing slash, are still valid. And why is this? Well, while it is true that every URI *must* contain a path, that path can be blank. In the case of URIs that contain an authority, the path must either be blank or begin with a slash, but blank paths are always acceptable unless the scheme defines otherwise. Many schemes seem to define a blank path as being equivalent to the a path consisting of a single slash, and that is the case with the https: and http: schemes. With my new URI-parsing tools that I am working on, I may store blank-path URIs in my database instead of single-slash path URIs.

It seems that on Saturday, I will be volunteering to be a pretend victim for an emergency preparedness educational meeting. On Sunday, I will likely be headed back to Springfield to do more cleaning and sorting.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

from __future__ import braces

Day 00327: Thursday, 2016 January 28

I prefer PHP as my learning tool. Despite it having major issues, it is very easy to add debug lines in PHP. Python has some strangeness that does not belong in a language, such as import antigravity. As a language, Python is not a regular tool like Aptitude is. While a small easter egg fits in quite well in Aptitude, anything that cannot be used in a program does not belong in a language. Overall though, it is a very nice language, or at least that is what I thought until today. Today though, wowaname showed me something that changed my mind about Python.

She showed me the from __future__ import braces statement. I was ecstatic! Upon first glance, it looks like this line would allow me to use a curly brace syntax instead of forced indention. While the forced indention may make final code look better, but is quite inconvenient when you want to insert a print line into the code for debugging, just to remove it moments later. With this new tool in hand, my path was clear. I would write my code with curly braces, using the easier syntax during development. Later, when my code had most of the bugs worked out, I would remove the curly braces and import line, causing Python to once again enforce clean-looking code in my functioning product. I was going to translate the beginnings of my spider into Python and use Python as my main language for future projects, with an exception for projects that generate Web pages, as I still feel that PHP has better Web server integration. However, when I tried using the statement from __future__ import braces, I was greeted with a condescending message: not a chance. Python is mocking people that want to use a braced syntax! If they wrote something about braced syntax being inferior in the manual or something in an effort to convince people that their way is better, that would be one thing. However, they actually wrote this feature into the language itself just to mock people that disagree with them!

In the span of a few minutes, I have gone from thinking that Python is a very nice language to having quite a disdain for it. I now will refuse to write anything in Python. It seems that I no longer have any of my Python scripts stored on my remote Git accounts. I may have taken them off of GitHub when I found NotABug.org, then never uploaded them to my NotABug.org account. In any case though, they will not be reuploaded until I translate them into a less condescending language, such as PHP.

To be clear though, while I refuse to write in Python any more, I am not outright boycotting all Python code or attempting to get other people to switch languages. If there is some functional code that someone wrote in Python, I will be more than happy to run it using my still-installed Python interpreter. Python is still a free software, cross-platform language. Every language has its issues, and it makes no sense to boycott software based on what language it is written in, assuming that software written in that language run in a free software environment and the language is efficient enough to avoid causing resource concerns. I simply would rather write code in a language that is more to my liking.

Someone pretended to be me and registered a Netflix account using my email address. I have added this "adan play" and Netflix to my hall of shame. As usual, I performed a password reset to lock the impostor out of the account. After resetting the password, I was able to see what service plan had been registered for. Unfortunately for adan, he registered for a $159 USD per month service, and now has no way to cancel the service. He may need to get ahold of Netflix somehow, in which case he will need to explain that he provided someone else's contact information instead of his own. If that does not work, he may need to cancel his credit card. I think that the lesson here is clear: when registering an account, use your own contact information, not the contact information of someone else. If you use someone else's email address to register an account, they can lock you out of your account. Using invalid contact information, such as the email address example@invalid.invalid is one thing, but when you use a valid email domain, you are asking for trouble.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

A class action against PayPal!

Day 00328: Friday, 2016 January 29

I thried to start working on my FAFSA application form, but it turned out that I needed an account elsewhere (the Federal Student Aid website) in order to register for FAFSA. At the Federal Student Aid website though, I ran into issues. The registration form uses JavaScript to disable pasting into certain fields. What nonsense is that? First of all, webmasters should not disable this vital functionality. It is none of the webmaster's business whether I type or paste. More importantly though, webmasters should not even be *able* to disable the pasting functionality. Pasting is done entirely client-side; the server does not even know if data has been typed or pasted. Instead, they instruct the client machine to disable it on the website's behalf. However, the client machine should listen to its actual owner ahead of the webmaster. If the user explicitly enters the paste command when a field is selected, anything short of pasting means that the machine is not doing what it should be.

I decided to take a quick break, and instead of giving in to the obnoxious website, find a way to disable this antifeature that is present in my own Web browser. The first useful search result was a plugin called Disable clipboard manipulations. I quickly looked over the license, then the description, and found that it is a free plugin that is supposed to prevent JavaScript from *listening* to cut, copy, and paste events. I decided to try it anyway, hoping that it would also block interference, and it thankfully did. It seems like overkill, as I only need to disable paste interference, not cut and copy interference, but I doubt that it will be an issue. Later, I came back to the add-on description page, and found that I had not read the description as throughly as I should have. First, the longer description does say that it prevents these events from being listened to, but the short description confirms that this plugin prevents interference. Second, the short description explains that this functionality has now been built into Firefox, one just needs to access the settings panel and adjust the dom.event.clipboardevents.enabled setting. This obsoletes the plugin, so I removed it, but I think that this plugin may be why it was added to the built-in functionality. This plugin has served its purpose.

I returned to the Federal Student Aid website, this time able to paste as I should be able to, and filled out the required form. I did not get a chance to fill out the FAFSA application though, due to being wisked off to work in my mother's classroom.

Before our mother came home, she sent Vanessa several SMS messages. However, they did not all come through, leading to a misunderstanding between Vanessa and our mother. Once she got home, the misunderstanding was cleared up quite quickly, but I am thankful that the messages had not gotten through. Our mother always seems to be under the impression that SMS is the most superior form of distance communication, to the point where email-to-SMS and SMS-to-email, both with her on the SMS side, are not good enough for her. She messages Vanessa when she wants to get ahold of Cyrus, as he often does not carry his mobile. His is not bound to his mobile the same way our mother is bound to hers. However, she also messages Vanessa when she wants to get ahold of me, even though I carry mine, because she does not want to send SMS to or receive SMS from my email address. When SMS utterly fails on her like this, it makes me happy because I hope that maybe she will learn to see that perhaps SMS is not as wonderful as she seems to think that it is. Once she arrived home and the misunderstanding was cleared up, Vanessa, Cyrus, and I went to her school to work on her classroom for mst of the day.

I received an email about a class-action settlement against PayPal. I was so excited! PayPal is having to pay for the fact that they were closing people's accounts, suspending people's accounts, improperly handled charge disputes, and and put reserves on accounts. In 2014 September, which was during the time period in question, PayPal began repeatedly suspending my account, claiming that I needed to prove my identity to them. Repeatedly, I complied more than was reasonable. They kept demanding that I provide photographs of my state-issued ID and Social Security card, copies of my credit card statements, copies of my utility bills with my name on them, an SMS-enabled telephone number that they could verify, and unfettered access to my bank account. Repeatedly, I provided photographs of my ID and Social Security card, despite the fact that I did not want to provide the Social Security card. Repeatedly, I provided copies of my credit card statements. Repeatedly, I told them that I do not have telephone service, so I cannot provide a telephone number, and that I do not pay for the utilities here, so there does not exist a utility bill with my name on it. And repeatedly, I told them that they had no business having access to my bank account, as I always payed via credit card when using PayPal, never bank withdraws. Every time, they claimed that they had reviewed my information and had decided to unlock my account, but upon logging in, it would immediately become suspended again. As I had kept telling them too, I only needed access to the account long enough to close the account, as they refused to close it with it suspended and they refused to allow me to make payments with my card that was attached to the account while not logged in. It took until near the end of January or February before they finally just deleted the account and freed my card. It was quite an ordeal, and it makes me hot headed again just typing about it. However, when I tried to submit a claim, I found two issues. First, they required a telephone number. I provided one of the standard dead numbers that is supposed to remain permanently unallocated, as the field could not be left blank or contain letters. Second, I had to submit proof of my claim. Proof lies in my old email inbox, the one that I lost in February when my hard drive died and I lost all my passwords, meaning that i lost all my accounts such as my email account. I actually managed to excavate a copy of my old password database from my mobile at some point, but it was not up to date. It lacked the key needed by Authenticator, so while it had the email password, I was still unable to get in.

Being reminded of my old PayPal account, I also remembered my new one. I started a new PayPal business account, having been told that doing so would allow me to make payments that come from a name matching my URI instead of coming from my name. However, PayPal required my to input the last four digits of my Social Security number, then kept complaining that they were wrong. I was entering the correct numbers, but for whatever reason, PayPal was refusing it. I went back today to try again, but found that I had not stored my password. I think that I had thought that the account did not get created because they would not let me finish with the form, but they had created it and had kept pestering me with emails since. I tried to reset my password, but PayPal insisted that I do so via telephone, so I was unable to do that. Coming back and investigating more later though, I found an alternative hidden password reset page. First, you have to tell the PayPal website that it was your email address that you forgot, not your password. Then, you need to tell it that you were kidding, and that you know your own email address, you just forgot the password. It will then ask for your social security number, then send you a password reset email. This did something that fixed my account though. Once PayPal had my Social Security number, they quit telling me that the last four digits are wrong when I enter them. Though I did still have to complete registration by providing the last four digits, this time, they were accepted. Resetting my password was a pain though. PayPal refused to allow me to paste my password, despite having disabled the interference of cut/copy/paste events in my configuration. I tried reinstalling that plugin from earlier, and that did not fix it either. Somehow, PayPal has found a way to disable pasting in an abnormal way. I defeated their restriction with KeePassX's auto-type feature, but PayPal still should not have this kind of power over my Web browser. Once I was in the account, I found that it likely does not meet my needs. It allows you to set how your business name appears when you charge someone's card, and I imagine that if the name on your credit card is not used when you are being charged yourself, this setting is used, not the setting that determines what your actual business' name is. This setting will only allow capicatl letters and spaces, no non-alphabetic symbols such as colons, slashes, and dots. If my suspicion is correct, a business PayPal account does me no good whatsoever, and accountless transactions are the better option.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.1 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Disaster relief first responders

Day 00329: Saturday, 2016 January 30

A couple people on Twitter were trying riled up in a frenzy about wowaname, who had apparently banned them from her channel. It all seemed well and good, seeing as wowaname does have a tendency to actively try to piss people off. However, they started attacking her claiming that she is not a woman and that she is having an identity crisis. Being transgendered is *not* the same thing as having an identity crisis. In an identity crisis, one cannot figure out who they are, and is having to search. On the other hand, transgendered people know who they are, society just tries to define these peopel differently than they define themselves. If they want to fight with wowaname, that is one thing. She brings it on herself. However, it is not okay to attack the transgendered community in the process with such claims.

Between several things that have been happening, I think that I have decided to try setting up an IRC server again. I will probably use the the ngIRCd package that I like and that I can get working without issues, then use a non-packaged services package that I would rather not use, but which would fulfill my obligation to keep channels somewhat under the control of the channel owners.

Later during the day, my mother and I pretended to be victims for a group of disaster relief first responders. We ran through an earthquake/tsunami scenario, after which, the first response team went over what they did right and what they did wrong. After that, we did it again, this time with improvements. The first response team said that anyone could join their team, but mentioned an icky part. They require a copy of your photo ID and Social Security card. They have no business having that. They are asking for volunteers. They have no right to demand that volunteers submit to identity verification. My mother asked thought that I might be interested, but when she asked and I declined, she knew exactly why without me having said anything. She was frustrated that I was concerned with giving out identifying documents. She claims that I am causing myself to miss out on things this way, but she does not seem to understand. I think that next time that she makes such a comment, I will provide an example that might get my point across. If she had to smear dog feces all on her face to join the team, she no doubt would want to join. I am the same way with identification documents. I am the same way with non-vegan food. And I am the same way with nonfree software and music. Yes, I am cutting myself off from things, but I am cutting myself off from things that I do not want in the first place. She cuts herself off from music and foods that she does not like as well.

Tomorrow, my mother and I might be going to some sort of trivia challenge at a bowling ally, though I do not know the details of it. It seems that we will not be headed to Springfield tomorrow though, whether we attend the trivia challenge or not.

Wowaname built a script for WeeChat a while back called embellish.py. This script is used to add fun colors and border characters to your text when typing on IRC. Many people on #Volatile. I finally started using it myself now. Wowaname even added a new feature for me: a channel whitelist. Previously, people have been using the script mostly everywhere, the blacklisting channels run by people that are bothered by it. The new whitelist allows me to use it only on the Volatile network though. I can have off be the default state of the script, and have it turned on only on channels that I know that people will not mind it on in.

My canary still sings the tune of freedom and transparency.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.

Ridiculous and hypocritical

Day 00330: Sunday, 2016 January 31

It is in great sadness that I take my leave from IRC. For a time, I will be secluding myself. I could be back tomorrow, or I could be back a year from now. I simply do not know. I will likely also be removing myself from any trivial online activity. I simply do not have the time and energy to spare right now. I have taken my canary down as well, and now I take my leave.

This morning started out well, but quickly turned sour. My mother asked for help with her classroom, but as we were walking out the door, she flipped out, told me that she did not want me to come, then freaked out about several unrelated topic, telling me off about each one.

Once more, she is trying to push the idea that asexuality is somehow a choice on my part, which does not make a bit of sense. Celibacy is the act of abstaining from sex, but asexuality is a state of not wanting it to begin with. I lack the instinct to desire sex, and that is not something that I could have chosen. She also has such warped views on privacy. She thinks that I should quit trying to protect my privacy, both online and out in the world, yet she tries to hid even the smallest and most insignificant details about everything from her ex-husband, just to be vindictive to him. For example, we have an open window on our front door. It has beveled glass, so it is difficult to see through though, so she feels safe allowing light to come through. However, whenever her ex-husband, my father, comes to pick up or drop off Vanessa and Cyrus, she blocks the windows with a curtain, just for home, then takes it down when she leaves. Her ex-husband is a small fry compared to the NSA. There is nothing that he is going to do if he happens to catch a glimpse of the inside of our home. The NSA on the other hand is intentionally running dragnet surveillance on the whole country and our citizens, violating the rights granted to us by the constitution in the process. Idiotically, she also has a problem with me carrying a bag to transport basic objects that I might need with me, such as my drink, my flashlight, my wallet, et cetera. She claims that if I had a car, I could use that instead. She somehow thinks that a car is a replacement for a bag! A better comparison would be comparing my bag to her purse. She uses a car, and yet she still uses a separate purse, a bag, to transport the items that she thinks that she will need. It is pure lunacy. Speaking of my drink, she wants me to stop carrying one, even though she carries a drink everywhere. Somehow, the fact that I try to stay hydrated is an embarrassment to her. Not carrying a drink leads to issues later in the day, but we will get back to that. She asked me if I was satisfied with life, so I told he mostly, but that there are a few things that I did not like. I listed both the fact that I have been unable to find a job and the fact that I cannot talk to her on any personal level without her freaking out on me over things that should not matter to her. As an example, I listed my choice in music. She has expressed the fact that she does not like it, so I keep my music out of her life. I listen to it only when we are apart and/or I have headphones. Yet somehow, my choice in music is offensive to her. After hearing that, she tried to justify it! She tried to claim that she is in the right to be against my music, even if I keep it out of her life! She claims that as long as I am using freedom as a factor in determining what goes in my music library, instead of sound alone, I am doing something wrong and I need to stop. She claims that I am being extreme, but it seems to me that she is being a control freak. She claims that freedom has no value and should be discarded. It saddens me, but I do not think that we can ever see eye-to-eye. She claims that I can speak with her on a personal level, but she makes it clear in her ridiculous arguments against anything I care about, just because I care about it, that I cannot. Next, she went onto the topic of carbon footprints. It bothers here that I try to keep mine down. She says that everyone, myself included, has a carbon footprint, and that I need to get over it. She does not seem to understand the difference between reducing a carbon footprint and eliminating it entirely. It is true, short of killing myself, I cannot eliminate my carbon footprint. However, that does not meant that I should not try to keep it as small as I can! Lastly, or at least the last thing that I remember in this ridiculous list of attacks on my character, she does not like that I have found friends that do not share her ideals. Anyone with differing ideals is the enemy to her, and they have "corrupted" me. Well, I suppose that she will not have to deal with that for a while.

She and I both agreed that I need to leave. She wants me to wait until she figures out if she is staying in the area. In what I assume is an act of mercy or pity, she "does not want to leave me stranded here". I am going to spend whatever free time I have trying to prepare for life on my own, such as apartment hunting and job hunting. I may also cool my head a bit with some continued code work. I will not have time to socialize or speak with friends for the time being though, which will probably make her happy.

After leaving without me and going to her classroom alone, she saw how much work that she had left to accomplish, and decided that she did want help after all. After making me jump through ridiculous hoops, she brought me to the school, though without my usual drink. I ended up dehydrated as expected, and wound up with a killer headache as a result. Meanwhile, she had her drink available to prevent herself from suffering the same fate. This is just ridiculous.

My canary has been shut down today. It has been replaced with a notice explaining that it will no longer be updated, but that the lack of updates is not caused by a gag order.

Copyright © 2016 Alex Yst; You may modify and/or redistribute this document under the terms of the GNU GPLv3+. If for some reason you would prefer to modify and/or distribute this document under other free copyleft terms, please ask me via email. My address is in the source comments near the top of this document. This license also applies to embedded content such as images. For more information on that, see licensing.

W3C standards are important. This document conforms to the XHTML 5.2 specification and uses style sheets that conform to the CSS3 specification.